<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against a careless indifferency in matters of religion. Being a treatise in opposition to those that believe, that all religions are indifferent, and that it imports not what men profess. / Done out of French. With an introduction by Anthony Horneck, D.D. Chaplain in ordinary to their Majesties.</title>
            <title>Traité contre l'indifférence des religions. English</title>
            <author>Pictet, Benedict, 1655-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04702)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2791:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against a careless indifferency in matters of religion. Being a treatise in opposition to those that believe, that all religions are indifferent, and that it imports not what men profess. / Done out of French. With an introduction by Anthony Horneck, D.D. Chaplain in ordinary to their Majesties.</title>
                  <title>Traité contre l'indifférence des religions. English</title>
                  <author>Pictet, Benedict, 1655-1724.</author>
                  <author>Horneck, Anthony, 1641-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 130 [i.e. 132] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Rhodes ..., and John Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the author's "Traité contre l'indifference des religions".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST A Careleſs Indifferency in Matters of RELIGION.</p>
            <p>Being a TREATISE In Oppoſition to thoſe that believe, That all Religions are Indifferent, and that it Imports not what Men Profeſs.</p>
            <p>Done out of French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With an</hi> INTRODUCTION <hi>by</hi> Anthony Horneck, <hi>D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Rhodes</hi> at the <hi>Star,</hi> the Corner of <hi>Bride Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet;</hi> and <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:2"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>WHile there is a <hi>City of God,</hi> and a <hi>City of the Devil,</hi> a <hi>Kingdom of Light,</hi> and a Kingdom of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> we muſt expect, that Truth and Virtue will be oppoſed by Sin, and Falſhood; and the more important any Truth is, the greater oppoſition it will meet with from, the <hi>inſtruments of Unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that reads the Hiſtory of the Church, will find how in every Age, one or other hath ſtarted up. to bark againſt the Light, and even then, when Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſhined, and Wonders were freſh, and Signs from Heaven accompanied the Doctrine; falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles transformed ſometimes into Angels of Light, have riſen, to undermine the Structure.</p>
            <p>There is not an Article of our Faith, but what hath been contradicted, and there is nothing ſo Sacred, but the Enemy of Mankind, hath found out perſons to ſerve him in the polluting it. Nor muſt we wonder, to find Truth aſſaulted, and its Beauty in danger of being ſullied. It would not look ſo Glorious if it were not reſiſted, and its Brightneſs doth in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, riſe, from <hi>the Quiver that rattles againſt it,</hi> from <hi>the glittering Spear and the Shield,</hi> The Darts thrown againſt it, ſhew its worth, and the rage of Enemies diſcovers its ineſtimable value; the price
<pb facs="tcp:179515:3"/>of the Treaſure is enhanced by the practices of Thieves, and that there are thoſe, who attempt the ſtealing of it, raiſes an appetite, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs in others, to embrace and keep it.</p>
            <p>Indeed, Truth like a Tree, runs out into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Branches, ſome whereof may be better ſpared, than others, and though, to cut the leaſt ſprig is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and injurious, yet, as in Human Bodies, a wound in the Arm, is not ſo pernicious as in the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and there is a vaſt difference between an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Head-ach, and a Diſeaſe that incroaches upon the Vitals; ſo while the leſſer Boughs of Truth are marred, though it may be the cauſe of juſt Grief, yet we can exerciſe that piece of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which <hi>beareth all things,</hi> but it is enough to put us out of all patience, to ſee the heart of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree levell'd at, and the Sap that feeds, and gives it life, in danger of being dried up.</p>
            <p>Such is the degeneracy of the Age we live in, that the very Fundamentals of Religion are ſtruck at, and though Modeſty was never any quality of the Devil, except it were in order to Deceive, yet his Boldneſs at this time ſeems to ſtep out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Road, and though <hi>Practical Atheiſm</hi> hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een the ſtratagem, he hath made uſe of all along, yet, his grand endeavour now, and of late years, is to lead Men into <hi>Speculative;</hi> And we ſee it hath ſo far prevailed with abundance of Men, that they are grown very <hi>Indifferent,</hi> whether they believe any thing at all, concerning God or Religion.</p>
            <p>As there is no error, but what Men pretend to give ſome reaſon for, ſo it's like the Lukewarmneſs of ſome, the horrid Debauchery of others, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb facs="tcp:179515:3"/>that are among Chriſtians, and the Animo-ſities of one party againſt another, and I will be bold to mention, the late Revolution too, or rather the miſconſtruction of it, may be alledged, as cauſes of this <hi>Indifferency.</hi> But where Men will not be at the pains of ſeparating the Droſs from the Gold, and are loath to diſtinguiſh the ill Digeſtion, from the goodneſs of the Food, or are for rejecting the uſe of things, becauſe they are managed ill by perſons, who Idolize their Intereſt, or which is as bad, from the irregularity of Practice, infer a falſity of Doctrine, they muſt neceſſarily run into ſtrange Conceits, and make that an Argument of unbelief, which ſhould engage them to a ſtricter Enquiry.</p>
            <p>We may juſtly look upon't, as a ſpecial Act of God's Providence, as <hi>Weeds</hi> do grow, ſtill to raiſe up Men to root them up, and to oppoſe the ſpreading Infection by ſuitable Antidotes. This he doth, though few take notice of it, that he may not leave himſelf without witneſs, and to render thoſe, who are willingly catcht with theſe deceitful Baits, inexcuſable. Indeed it is not every excuſe, will take with an All-intelligent Being, and for Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pretend, that they cannot be ſatisfied in the great Principles of Religion, which are to make them good, and ſerviceable to God and Man, either becauſe of the different Opinions about them, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ill uſe, that ſome make of them, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is hard to know the Truth, is a frivilous Plea when we ſee, they are more inquiſitive after things, which make againſt Religion, then after that, which can be ſaid for it, and wilfully neglect peruſing, and conſidering Books, which aſſert and vindicate the
<pb facs="tcp:179515:4"/>power of it, and greedily ſwallow the froth of witty Men, ſpew'd out againſt its force, and energy. Since Atheiſm and <hi>Indifferency</hi> have made thoſe incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon us, which to our Sorrow we behold, many admirable Treatiſes have come forth to baffle its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. But theſe are very carefully ſhun'd by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſer ſort, or if any ſuch be put into their hands, they are rejected with a <hi>Laugh,</hi> and a merry <hi>Jeſt</hi> takes with them more, then the moſt judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings.</p>
            <p>So f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd are Men of ruining themſelves, and ſcrape together, what traſh they can, to fortifie themſelves againſt ſubſtantial Goodneſs. However, God is kind, in affording them helps to free themſelves from the Devil's ſnares, and if thoſe Helps be wilfully reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is ſoon gueſſed, at whoſe door their Deſtruction will lye.</p>
            <p>Truth ſhall triumph at laſt, and all the prophane Herd ſhall find, when it is too late, it may be, they had a God to deal with, that will not be mocked. Since nothing can ſatisfie them, but experience of God's Juſtice, they ſhall find it to their coſt, and by intolerable anguiſh of Mind, be convinc'd of that which they would not be perſuaded to believe, by the cleareſt Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Good Lord! That there ſhould be a neceſſity of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pains to perſuade Men, that they are not Beaſts, and that their Reaſon, Capacities, and Powers of their Souls, require ſomething more then Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Sleeping, and minding their Buſineſs, and Pleaſures in the World! This hath been ſo fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtrated by Wiſe and Conſiderate Men, that one would think, there ſhould be no room left for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges,
<pb facs="tcp:179515:4"/>and Evaſions, and as ſuch perſons juſtly have thought, they could not employ their Talen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then in aſſerting the ſtrong foundations of Religion, ſo they deſerve. Eternal Commendations, for letting the World ſee, that whatever attempts have been made to ruine it, its pillars, like that of the Earth, are unmoveable, and its Notions ſo riveted into our Natures, that we muſt firſt deny our Being, before we can deny its Principles.</p>
            <p>The ſame I may ſay of the Author of theſe Papers, who obſerving the ſtrange <hi>Indifferency,</hi> that is abroad in the World, hath endeavour'd <hi>to daſh that Child againſt the ſtones.</hi> His Arguments are ſtrong, and weighty, and his Anſwers to the Cavils and Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Atheiſtical Men, ſhort, but pithy, and ſuch as may ſatisfie Men, who have not totally abandon'd the Dictates of right Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Religion is a thing fitted to our Reaſon, and the more our Reaſon is employ'd about it, the more its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and Beauty, and Glory will appear. That Men are ſo <hi>Indifferent</hi> about it, the principal cauſe is, becauſe rational Conſideration is excluded, and they are guided more by their Sences then their Reaſon. They are for the moſt part brought up, and educated into ſenſuality, and whatever grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies their Sences, is made the darling Object of their Love, and becauſe Religion lays a reſtraint upon the ſenſual Appetite, they are very willing to entertain prejudices againſt it, and any little exception ſerves as an Argument againſt ſubmitting to the Holy Laws of it. The de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per root this ſenſuality takes, the more Religion is weakened, and thruſt out, till in time the common Principles of it are queſtion'd, and
<pb facs="tcp:179515:5"/>at laſt, if it may be done with ſafety, as to the Law of the Land, denied.</p>
            <p>It's love to Vice, that corrupts Mens <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and if we examine and ſearch into the root of all, it will be found that this <hi>Indifferency</hi> in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion proceeds from Mens being addicted to ſome Sin, or other, they are loth to part with; and becauſe the ſtricter Rules of Religion, are inconſiſtent with their unbrideled Luſts, they think it their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to abandon it, or if they retain any thing of it, it is only a ſhadow, and no more.</p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo bad, but may be colour'd over with ſpecious Arguments, and unthinking Men are ſoon gravell'd with ſuch kind of Objections, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the byaſſe be toward evil; for then a very weak Argument will draw, and what it wants in ſtrength, is made up by the power of a vicious Inclination. This gives it weight, and makes that concluſive, which at other times would ſcarce deſerve a moment of ſerious Conſideration.</p>
            <p>That I recommend the peruſal of this Book, is not ſo much to gratifie the Book-ſeller, as to promote the publick Good; The Work is uſeful, and may help to reform the times, and put a ſtop to the growth of Licentiouſneſs. The meaneſt Reader may benefit himſelf by it, and it will furniſh him with Anſwers to the vulgar Objections of <hi>Libertines.</hi> The ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its Bulk will be an encouragement to look it over, and the ſolid Reaſons made uſe of, will by the Bleſſing of God convince him, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more in Religion, then <hi>Fancy.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. HORNECK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:5"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THere are ſo many People now a days, who believe, that all Religions are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, that 'tis not a thing to be wonder'd at, If ſomething in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſuch a growing Miſchief ſhould be written upon this ſubject. But we cannot forbear to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that there are five ſort of Perſons who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this Indifferency.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are ſome who do it purely out of Affection to Libertiniſm, and becauſe that Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally they love to be Independent. They will not acknowledge any Maſter over 'em, to the end they may be able to ſay, believe, and do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they pleaſe, without fearing to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others there are who do it out of Vanity; to the end they may be thought to be Wits of the Firſt Order, that diſdain to herd with thoſe that follow the Common Opinion. And theſe People at firſt are but weakly convinc'd of what they ſay; but by publiſhing continually their Singular Sentiments, they come to be fully perſuaded of the Truth of 'em at laſt, and haughtily ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Rank of the People diſabus'd, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with pity upon the Reſt of the World, that are ſcar'd with the thoughts of Futurity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:6"/>
            <p n="3">3. There are ſome who do it out of Sloth; becauſe they will not give themſelves the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Examining Religions. So that they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be eaſily ſurprized by the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our Pretended <hi>Soaring Wits;</hi> finding themſelves by that means delivered from the care they ought to take in a more diligent and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Scrutiny.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Others uphold this Opinion becauſe they find it very convenient for preſerving their Eſtates and their Honours, which they prefer before Truth, and love beyond all things in the World.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There are ſome who do it, not becauſe they believe all Religions to be Indifferent, but becauſe they have peculiar Sentiments of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they dare not ſow abroad until they have Inſinuated, that 'tis a very Indifferent thing what Men believe, that they may not offend 'em with their Opinions.</p>
            <p>That which is moſt to be Lamented is this, that theſe Wild Opinions very much corrupt and taint Others, which they do with ſo much the leſs trouble, 1. Becauſe that naturally we love Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and we would willingly be Independent. 2. Becauſe we are pufft up with Pride, and that there is nothing that pleaſes us ſo much as to be diſtinguiſh'd from others. 3. Becauſe labour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlikes us, and for that we love not that which puts us to any hardſhip. 4. Becauſe we have too great an Affection for our Wealth, and for that it is a great Trouble to us to quit the Pleaſures and Comfortable Conveniences of this Life. There is nothing left uneſſay'd to ſurprize thoſe Pious Souls that ſeek to work out their Salvation.
<pb facs="tcp:179515:6"/>There is great care taken to make 'em under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that they ought to make Chriſtian Morality their Study, and that there is nothing but Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality to be preach'd up. They tell us, that we have need to be corrected and reproved; that the Greateſt part of Men ſufficiently knows the Will of God, but that few practiſe it. This is agreed; but the Chief Aim of thoſe who thus diſcourſe, is artificially to inſinuate, that there is no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of tormenting our ſelves, about what we ought to believe, only that we ought to live well. And thus they prepare People inſenſibly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that all Religions are Indifferent. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we muſt acknowledge, that they who are of this Opinion are not all alike corrupt; but yet they are ſufficiently erroneous for us to deplore the Misfortune of this Age. 'Tis for the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to fortifie themſelves againſt thoſe Deluſions, that we have undertaken this Treatiſe, and with and endeavour to recall thoſe that are gone aſtray. This is the only aim that we have propoſed to our ſelves, and not to get the Reputation of an Author. We conjure all thoſe that read this Little Manual, to ſtrive with themſelves and to read it with Application. We beſeech 'em not to read it with a Libertine's Humour that Scoffs at every thing, but with a deſire to ſearch out the Truth, and with the ſame diligence that they ſtudy Human Sciences. Let 'em conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the diſpute is not here about a Thing of little Importance, ſince it concerns their being Eternally Miſerable if they are deceiv'd, as we ſhall make appear in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179515:7"/>
            <p n="2">2. Let 'em not reject what we ſhall ſay, under pretence of meeting with Reaſons that are not fully convincing. For thô there were but one good Reaſon in a Chapter, 'twere enough to oblige 'em to return from their Wandrings.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they ought not to deſpiſe the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, under pretence that they have heard 'em ſeveral times; but let 'em carefully examine 'em, and lay aſide their Prejudices.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, That it is not enough to find ſome petty fault, to reject the Reaſons which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; for that there is nothing ſo eaſie as to oppoſe ſome little Sophiſms to good Arguments. But let 'em conſult their own Conſciences: I moſt Heartily beſeech Almighty God to give a Bleſſing to my weak Endeavours.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 18. Line 18. for <hi>Sees,</hi> read <hi>Seems.</hi> page 30. l. 32. dele <hi>All.</hi> p. 31. l. <hi>ult.</hi> for <hi>in,</hi> r. <hi>with.</hi> p. 34. l. 12. for <hi>no Confuſion,</hi> r. <hi>nothing but Confuſion.</hi> pa. 42. l. 33. for <hi>King</hi> r. <hi>Kind.</hi> pa. 46. l. 22. for the firſt <hi>him,</hi> r. <hi>us.</hi> pa. 56. l. 31. for <hi>Proportions,</hi> r. <hi>Propoſitions.</hi> pa. 66. l. 19. for <hi>ſubſcribe,</hi> r. <hi>preſcribe.</hi> pa. 69. l. 12. for <hi>wearing</hi> r. <hi>drawing.</hi> for <hi>upon</hi> r. <hi>from.</hi> pa. 71. l. 2. for <hi>of her,</hi> r. <hi>other.</hi> pa. 74. l. 6. for <hi>has,</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> pa. 77. l. 8. Inſert <hi>Not.</hi> pa. 79. l. 18. for <hi>Animoſity,</hi> r. <hi>Animality.</hi> pa. 89. Chap. XV. for <hi>they make,</hi> r. <hi>they may make.</hi> pa. 90. l. 8. after <hi>ſtrong,</hi> inſert <hi>they.</hi> pa. 93. l. 4. for <hi>long,</hi> r. <hi>come.</hi> pa. 94. l. 26. for <hi>the things of Conſiſtence,</hi> r. <hi>Remorce of Conſcience.</hi> pa. 130. l. 32. for <hi>aſſert,</hi> r. <hi>aſſerts.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179515:7"/>
            <head>A TREATISE</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Againſt thoſe that believe that all Religions are Indifferent.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Wherein, after we have ſuppos'd that there is a God, we ſhew that God is moſt perfect. That he is the Author of all the Good which is in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and that we ought to Fear and Honour him.</head>
               <p>THE Being of a God is a Truth ſo Evident, that no Man can deny it without combating his own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. There's no neceſſity of ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Endeavours to believe it; for that Man muſt put a Violence upon himſelf, who dares to contradict it. For proof of it, there is no need of rommaging for Metaphyſical, high-flown, far fetch'd Arguments, ſcarcely within the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179515:8"/>Reach of moſt Men's Underſtanding. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this ſame ſpacious Univerſe expos'd to our Eyes, and all the Creatures we behold within it, together with the Correſpondency, the Symmetry and Relation of the ſeveral Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parts to the Whole, is ſufficient to convince all people that will liſten to their Reaſon. For as for thoſe that are not ſtruck with the ſenſible Marks which the Author of Nature has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed on his Works, they will never ſubmit to the Force of Diſpute. The moſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent, and moſt Learned of the<note n="*" place="margin">Cicero l. <hi>2.</hi> Nat. Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Romans was ſo over-rul'd by this particular Proof, that he makes no ſcruple to maintain, after a great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, that if Men ſhould of a ſudden, ſtart up from under the Earth, where they had remain'd in Darkneſs from the Time of their Birth, and all at once behold the Land, the Sea, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; the Beauty, the vaſt Body and wonderful Effects of the Sun, they would not fail to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a Deity, and to confeſs that the whole which they contemplated was the Workmanſhip of a God.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, either we muſt believe that the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is Eternal, or that the World is the Effect of Chance; or elſe we muſt acknowledge that there is an All-powerful Being which made both the one and the other. Now it cannot be ſaid, that a Dead and Inſenſible Maſs, ſuch as was the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is an Eternal Being, and without any Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, becauſe it would be the Greateſt of all Abſurdities, to aſcribe to the Vileſt of all Beings, the Chiefeſt of all Perfections, which is to exiſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179515:8"/>of it ſelf. Beſides, in regard that Motion is not Eſſential to the Matter, tho' it ſhould be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be Eternal, we ſhould be ſtill putting the Queſtion, when it began to have Motion? Who it was that gave it the firſt Impreſſions? Who it was that ſhap'd it into ſo many various Figures? Who made this Motion ſo juſt and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; and who it was that produc'd ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite variety of Creatures out of one and the ſame Matter? So that when all is done, we muſt come to one Sovereign Being, which we call GOD.</p>
               <p>It cannot be ſaid, that this Vaſt Univerſe is the Effect of Chance, or that it was the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Meeting of Certain little Bodies which produc'd it. The Pagan Philoſopher who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd this Opinion, that Nature muſter'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the Atomes of her Wiſdom to compoſe it, ſeems to me no leſs Extravagant in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular then He, who, beholding ſeveral Pictures, wherein were to be obſerv'd all the Rules of Exact and Elaborate Painting, and a great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Figures curiouſly drawn, ſhould ſay, that it was the Workmanſhip of Chance, or that the Colours mix'd ſo Artfully together of themſelves.</p>
               <p>What Man of ſound Judgment can be ſo vain to think, that it was <hi>Chance</hi> that made the <hi>Whole</hi> which we Contemplate, the Heavens, the Earth, the Sun, the Stars, the Plants and Animals; That it was <hi>Chance,</hi> that in the Wombs of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers form'd a Piece of Workmanſhip ſo perfect as that of our Bodies, whoſe Structure, Figure, Organs, Members, their wonderful Symmetry and juſt Proportion, is ſtill the Admiration of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179515:9"/>Human Wiſdom: that it was <hi>Chance.</hi> which produc'd our Souls; that Soul which thinks, which raiſes it ſelf above our Sences, and which corrects and govern 'em; that ſearches after, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents and finds out, thoſe things that ſeem'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for Human Reach. Laſtly, that it was <hi>Chance,</hi> which united this Soul ſo perfectly with the Body, that ſuch and ſuch motions of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſtir up Thoughts in the Soul, and ſuch and ſuch Thoughts of the Soul, which produce variety of Motions in the Body. Certainly we muſt no longer pretend to make uſe of our Reaſon, if we once deny theſe to be the Works of an All-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, moſt Wiſe, All-underſtanding, and moſt Perfect Being.</p>
               <p>So that I ſhall not undertake to refute thoſe, who in defence of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> adventure to bring ſome Examples of what <hi>Chance</hi> is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. For there is ſo little proportion between what they alledge, and the Creatures which we ſpeak of, that 'tis a wonder that People who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Wit, ſhould employ it in ſuch feeble Proofs. I might as eaſily prove, that becauſe it ſo happens, that three or four Letters may be ſo thrown together by chance, as to form a word; a Man might as eaſily make a Poem as accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd as <hi>Virgil</hi>'s <hi>Aeneads.</hi> Nay, thô I ſhould grant that <hi>Chance</hi> might form ſome one of thoſe Creatures which we every day admire; Shall we from thence infer, that it was <hi>Chance</hi> that ſo well order'd all things, as to preſcribe to every thing the particular Uſe that is aſſign'd it, or that ſo well joyn'd and plac'd together all things, as to be uſeful the one to the other, the Heavens to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179515:9"/>the Earth, the Earth to the Plants, the Plants to the Creatures? Thô <hi>Chance</hi> might frame an Eye, how is it poſſible for us to conceive, that <hi>Chance</hi> alſo made the Light, without which, the Eyes would ſignifie nothing?</p>
               <p>Seeing then that matter is not Eternal, and that the World was not made of it ſelf, either by <hi>Chance</hi> or the concurrence of Atoms, according to <hi>Epicurus,</hi> of neceſſity we muſt conclude, that there is an Almighty Being that made it, ſince no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an infinite Power could draw the firſt Matter out of Nothing, or give it ſo lovely a Form. And this All Powerful Being is that which we call God.</p>
               <p>It may be objected perhaps, that Nature is the cauſe of all thoſe Great Effects; 'tis ſhe, ſay they, that cauſes the Plants to ſprout and ſhoot forth, that gives Life to Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But all this while, what do they mean by Nature? Is it an Intelligent Cauſe? or a Blind and Stupid Cauſe? If it be a Stupid Cauſe, how comes it to act with ſo much Wiſdom? If it be an Intelligent Cauſe, endu'd with infinite Wiſdom, is not this the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Nature that which we call God? Or if they mean by Nature, that Order which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Production, Generation and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of every Creature; then who eſtabliſh'd that Order, but that ſovereign Being which we all adore?</p>
               <p>'Tis then moſt certain that there is a <hi>God;</hi> and we have no deſign to enlarge any farther upon the proof of it. All Sciences lead us to this Truth, and all Nations in all Ages have acknowledg'd it, except ſome certain barbarous People among
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179515:10"/>whom Reaſon was almoſt extinguiſh'd; and in ſome, Travellers have not obſerv'd any ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Deity, becauſe they have not been ſo ſtrictly nice to inform themſelves. But Man, who is naturally proud and high-minded, has ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſen to worſhip Wood and Stones, Beaſts and Plants, Crocodils and Trees, Rats and Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then to be without a God, and adore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all. However, we muſt confeſs, that there were formerly, and ſtill are now-a-days, ſome People, who making an ill uſe of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, attacque this Principle and drawing off their Wit from every thing that might be able to prove a Deity, meerly to apply themſelves to whatever may increaſe and harden 'em in their Doubts, perſuade themſelves at length, that there is no God. But beſides, that they who arrive to this degree of Impiety, are not very numerous; and that there is great reaſon to queſtion, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any real Atheiſts; I ſpeak of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts in Wit, if I may preſume ſo to expreſs my ſelf, and not of Atheiſts in Heart, there are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few who carry their incredulity to their Grave. The greateſt part confeſs in deſpite of their own Teeth, the Deity, whoſe Enemy they declare themſelves to be; nor can they forbear implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Aid in their moſt preſſing occaſions, and upon unexpected Accidents; neceſſity and their Conſcience forcing 'em to acknowledge, what before out of malice and diſdain of Heav'n they deny'd. Therefore the Impiety of ſome Libertines, who endeavour to prove there is no God, becauſe they could wiſh there were not,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179515:10"/>ought not be any inducement for us to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion a Verity ſo univerſally acknowledg'd.</p>
               <p>But if it behoves our Reaſon as Haughty as it is, to confeſs a Deity, and that Man has a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, under whoſe Empire it becomes him to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf; it becomes him alſo to acknowledge that this Sovereign Power poſſeſſes all Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thoſe in ſuch a degree, as that there can be none conceiv'd to be greater or more accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd.</p>
               <p>This is the <hi>Idea</hi> which we naturally have of God; nor can we have any other, if we follow the Illuminations of Right Reaſon. Nothing is to be conceiv'd to be better, or more perfect then the Deity; and this is agreed on by all the World. For if he wanted ſome Perfection, or if he did not poſſeſs it in a Supream degree, then would ſomething be conceiv'd more perfect then He. Therefore it muſt be own'd, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſpeaks of a God, ſpeaks of the moſt perfect of all Beings, that exiſt or can exiſt.</p>
               <p>I will not undertake to deſcribe all theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; they are Infinite: nor can the Angels themſelves, thoſe Bleſſed Exiſtencies, who are always before this Sovereign Being, but very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly inſtruct us who he is. 'Tis ſufficient that we obſerve that no Man can have an <hi>Idea</hi> of a moſt perfect Being, without conceiving at the ſame time, that he ſubſiſts of himſelf, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily exiſts; that he is an Eternal Being, and without any, Beginning: that he is an Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Being, but upon whom all things depend: an All-ſeeing, All-knowing, All-foreſeeing, and Omnipotent Exiſtence. A Being Sovereignly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179515:11"/>good, moſt Juſt, moſt Wiſe, and moſt Happy. Thus it behoves us to conceive all theſe Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Being which we adore, and who is our God.</p>
               <p>This is a Truth beyond all Conteſt: But it is alſo no leſs certain, that this moſt perfect Being, who created the Matter, the World, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we behold contain'd within it, is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all the Good which is in the Creatures. All the Creatures can expect no Good, but from him who gave 'em their Being, and by whom they ſubſiſt. There is none but He who perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knows what is convenient for 'em, becauſe he knows all things; and He alone can only beſtow it upon 'em, by reaſon of his Omnipotency. The Pagans have acknowledg'd this, in the midſt of their Ignorance, as it would be eaſie for me to prove out of the Works of their moſt celebrated Authors. They all agreed, that their Lives and their good Fortune (for that was their manner of ſpeaking) depended upon God. <hi>This is the Opinion of all Men,</hi> ſaid <hi>Cicero:</hi> for I mind not what <hi>Ajaz</hi> ſays in <hi>Sophocles,</hi> and another no leſs impious in <hi>Eſchylus,</hi> who upheld, that none but Fools and faint-hearted People implor'd the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency of the Gods. But there have been others who have added, that Wiſdom and Virtue depended upon this Supream Being; that the Beginning and End, or the ſucceſs of all Things depended upon him: And the Emperor <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus</hi> has thoſe ſentiments upon this Subject, as put to ſhame ſeveral falſe Chriſtians. For he ſays, that there is an Effectual Virtue in God, which acts in us, and operates all our good
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179515:11"/>Actions, and all our good deſires, and which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves from us all Opportunities and Occaſions of falling into Sin.</p>
               <p>From all theſe Truths I draw this Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which naturally flows from theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; That it is abſolutely our Duty to Honour this Infinite Being, to endeavour from day to day to underſtand him more perfectly, continually to admire his Virtues, to love and fear him, to make it our whole imployment to pleaſe him, and ſo to bear our ſelves, that whatever we are, what ever we do, whatever we have, may be all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to his Glory. For let us but grant that there is a God in the World, that this God is moſt perfect, that he is Supreamly Good, and that he is the Author of all the Good which we enjoy, and of all that we can hope for; certainly we cannot then forbear to admire his Perfections, but muſt believe our ſelves engag'd and bound to love him. Let us but acknowledge that this God is Omnipotent, and that it is in his Power to reduce all the Creatures he has made, into their Primitive Duſt, and that he is able Eternally to puniſh thoſe who violate his Laws, we muſt be then aſſuredly convinc'd, that he is to be fear'd, and we ought not to provoke his Wrath. Let us be perſuaded that this God is moſt Juſt, that he loves Juſtice, and that whatever he exacts from us, tends only to make us happy, and is nothing but what is moſt conformable to ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> real Intereſts, it creates a Pleaſure in us to obey him, and be ſubmiſſive to his Will. Let us once be ſenſible, that this God is both able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to redreſs all our Complaints, to deliver us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179515:12"/>out of all our Miſeries, and that all things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon his Conduct and Direction, it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently perſuades us to a ſole Reliance upon him. Laſtly, Let us believe that this God is moſt Wiſe, that he Created Man for thoſe ends which are moſt worthy of him, and we can never queſtion, but that Men are bound to purſue thoſe ends to which they are appointed, in making a right uſe of that Reaſon which they have receiv'd, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying it to the Glory of him who gave it 'em. Now all theſe Acts of Veneration, Reſpect, Fear, Submiſſion, Adoration, Admiration, Confidence, Obedience, and Love, are comprehended in the ſingle Word <hi>Religion.</hi> So that the Idea and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, imports the Neceſſity of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That Religion is not the Invention of Politicians.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome People who maintain that Religion, as alſo the Opinion of a God, is the Invention of certain Politicians, who, as they ſuppoſe, made the People believe there is a Deity, on purpoſe to retain 'em in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Obedience; that there is a certain Worſhip to be paid him; and that this Deity ſeverely puniſhes the Treacherous, the Seditious, and Rebels.</p>
               <p>But it will be no difficult thing to make out the abſurdity of this Opinion to thoſe who have any Love and Veneration for Truth. For to prove,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179515:12"/>that there were any Legiſlators, or any cunning Politicians, who made the People believe that there is a God, and that there is a Neceſſity of a Religion, they muſt make it appear to us,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That before the Birth of thoſe Legiſlators, and Founders of States and Dominions, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were ignorant that there was a God, and that they never paid him any Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="1">2. That thoſe Legiſlators never had themſelves any Fear or Sentiment of a Deity.</p>
               <p>Now this is that which they will never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove; neither do I believe they will ever preſume to undertake it. Let 'em inſtance any time wherein People liv'd without acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a God. Let 'em tell us the Names of thoſe firſt Men, that were the Authors of that Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that there is a Deity; at leaſt let 'em inſtruct us when thoſe Ages were, that it firſt began to be receiv'd in the World. 'Tis true, it cannot be deny'd but that there were ſome Politicians who have made advantagious uſe of this Firſt Notion, That there is a Being who is far Superiour to all thoſe which we behold, or of which we have any knowledge, as they have no leſs ſucceſsfully made uſe of the Vanity of the People, and that love which they naturally have for Liberty, their Lives, their Children, or whatever elſe belongs to 'em: and of this Number were <hi>Jeroboam, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Lycurgus, Solon, Numa, Mahomet,</hi> and ſome others famous in Hiſtory. I muſt acknowledge likewiſe that theſe Legiſlators very much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd the People in their Natural Propenſity to a Religion; in regard they had too much Wit to be Ignorant, that without Religion Society would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179515:13"/>degenerate into Common Robbery, ſince every one would then do what he pleas'd; the moſt Crafty would be the moſt Wiſe, and the moſt Powerful and ſtrongeſt would be always Maſters. 'Tis moſt certain alſo, that theſe Law-givers have made the People believe, that the Deity would be Worſhip'd in ſuch or ſuch a Manner; and that they have introduc'd ſuch Ceremonies as they thought moſt proper for their Deſigns. Nor will I ſcruple to agree, that there have been ſeveral who derided the Deities which the People ador'd, and who have made 'em pay their Adoration to what Deities they pleas'd. The thing was eaſie to be done in ſuch Places, where the People were ignorant of the True God whom they were to ſerve. But I aver, that never any of thoſe Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators undertook to prove the Exiſtence of a God. They took that Truth for Granted, and built upon that Foundation. But they never prov'd it; and I am aſſuredly convinc'd, that if they had not met with it already engrav'd in the Hearts and Minds of all Men, they would never have ſucceeded in their Great Deſigns.</p>
               <p>Is it a thing to be believ'd, that two or three Men could deceive the whole World, or that for the Eſtabliſhment of their Authority, they could ever impoſe their own Inventions upon People as Quick-ſighted as themſelves, that Laugh'd at Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Errors, ſuch as <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> or <hi>Cicero?</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it probable, that they could have ſeduc'd and miſled People who were not ſubjected to their Dominion; nay, People that commanded over others, to believe the Flatteries of thoſe who would needs perſuade 'em that their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179515:13"/>and Princes were Gods, and whom indeed they Worſhip'd as ſo many Deities? Is it poſſible an Opinion, Originally no more then the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome Ambitious Perſons, ſhould be ſo deeply rooted in the minds of all Men, that they could never Eradicate it again, whatever efforts they made, when we find every day that Men renounce ſo many Vulgar-Errors, tho' ſuck'd in with their Infant Milk?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Is there any Appearance or Likelihood, that after ſo many Ages, Men ſhould never be Convinc'd of an Opinion that diſquiets and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiles their Conſciences with ſo many Terrors and Convulſions?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Indifference of Religions.</head>
               <p>TIs clear then, that all Men have a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inclination to Religion, in regard that All have an Opinion that there is a God. Now if they all underſtood this Deity after one and the ſame Manner, there would be but one Religion in the World. But their Idea's are ſo various, that there are almoſt as many Religions as there are People. From whence the Queſtion has riſen, Whether Men are equally acceptable to God, whatever Religion they profeſs? And whether they may be allow'd, as an Indifferent Thing, to be of any Religion? There are ſome People, and of theſe too many, God knows, who believe that all Religions are Indifferent: that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179515:14"/>the Chief Religion, is to be Obedient to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates that Govern us; that God is in truth the Center to which all our Devotion ought to tend, but that it is of little Importance which way Men arrive at that Center, provided they get thither; and that there are ſeveral ways to be happy. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no itinere non poſſe perveniri ad tam grande Secretum,</hi> according to <hi>Symmachus.</hi> That we ought to be of the Religion of the People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom we live, and not to tye our ſelves to any one particular manner of ſerving God, but to be initiated into all ſorts of Religions, <hi>Eſſe totius Mundi Sacrorum Antiſtitem,</hi> as a Pagan ſaid. They who have given us Relations of the Belief of the <hi>Siamois,</hi> or People of <hi>Siam,</hi> report, that they believe, That God does not preſerve the World, but only for the ſake of that Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement and pleaſure which he takes in the Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Languages, Creatures, Habits, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions; that this ſame Medley produces the ſame Effect as the Diverſity of Flowers in a Garden, the difference of Meats at a Banquet, or the Diſtinction of Offices in a Princes Palace; for that in like manner God delights himſelf with inſpiring into Mortals ſeveral manners of Adoring and Serving him; and that we ought to believe 'em all to be good, ſince they have all the ſame Object, and bring Man home to his laſt End. 'Tis alſo ſaid, That the King of <hi>Siam</hi> made Anſwer to the Perſon who propos'd to him, in the Name of an Ambaſſador from a Great Prince, his turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian, <hi>That he wonder'd, the Prince ſhould ſo much trouble himſelf in a buſineſs relating to God, for which it did not appear that God did any way
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179515:14"/>concern himſelf, as having left it wholly to our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. For,</hi> added he, <hi>the True God, who Created Heav'n and Earth and all the Creatures therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and who has given 'em Natures and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo different, had he ſo pleas'd, at the ſame time, that he gave Men Bodies and Souls alike, could have infus'd into 'em the ſame ſentiments of the Religion which they were to profeſs, and have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited all Nations under one Law. But,</hi> continued he, <hi>'tis obvious that Providence permits diverſity of Sects and Opinions, becauſe that God takes as much delight to be ador'd with different Forms of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Ceremonies, as to be glorifi'd by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Variety of Creatures, whoſe ſundry Beauties publiſh his Infinite Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in regard, there are too too many among thoſe who call themſelves Chriſtians, who with Banners diſplay'd, appear in defence of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, concerning the Indifferency of Religion, Our deſign is to Combat 'em in the following Chapters. But firſt of all it behoves us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that they who are of this Opinion, do not all uphold it after one and the ſame manner. There are ſome who deny Providence; others who will not have it to be concern'd in Matters of Religion. There are ſome who aſſert the Mortality of our Soul: Others aver, that to ſpeak properly, there is no ſuch thing as <hi>True</hi> or <hi>Falſe, Juſt</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt;</hi> but that every thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Will of Man. There are ſome who believe, that Truth lies ſtill in Darkneſs, and that God has not reveal'd it; Others, that he has reveal'd it, but ſo obſcurely, that there is no Hereſie which may not be prov'd by the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179515:15"/>Word of God. Others maintain that Peace is to be preferr'd before Truth; and altogether cry up the great Good which would redound to the World from the Opinion of Indifferency in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Were but this Opinion every where re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, they ſay, there would be no more Wars about Religion, nor any more Contentions about Myſteries of Faith. All Men would live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in perfect Unity, and this Lower World would be a Little Heaven. They extol the firſt Author of this Opinion as one that never can be too Highly applauded, and erect Monuments and Statues to honour his Memory. All Men, they Cry, ought to give God continual Thanks for ſending ſuch a Man into the World, and at the ſame time are ſtrangely troubl'd becauſe he was not Immortal. Let us now ſee whether this Opinion merits ſo many Elogies, or rather, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it deſerve not publick Execration. And to the end, that none may have reaſon to complain, let us take all our <hi>Indifferents</hi> (for I beg the favour that I may have leave to call 'em ſo) one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and let us impartially examine what they hold forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:179515:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Againſt thoſe who deny a Providence.</head>
               <p>I Shall begin with thoſe, who, not daring to maintain that there is no God, yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to deny his Providence, and aſſent with <hi>Epicurus,</hi> that the Supream Deity never concerns himſelf with what is acted upon Earth: That 'tis a thing beneath the Grandeur of a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Being, to take cognizance of the Petty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Mortals here below; and ſo 'tis very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to Him of what Religion they are.</p>
               <p>True it is, that altho' the Love which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us to have for Truth, ſhould always oblige us to ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelves up to the Belief of that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which is moſt conformable to our receiv'd <hi>Idea</hi>'s of God; nevertheleſs it muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, that if there were no Providence, we might conclude it needleſs for Man to torment himſelf about Religion; and deem it lawful enough to make choice of that which beſt agrees with our Intereſts, or with the Society with which we converſe. But 'tis no difficult thing to refute this Opinion, which, with as good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon might be call'd, <hi>The Sponge of all Religions,</hi> as a Perſian Author once ſaid the ſame thing of the <hi>Fatality of the Stoicks.</hi> Nor ſhall I make uſe of any more then two or three Arguments to overthrow it, without alledging any paſſages out of Scripture, becauſe I diſpute with People that will not acknowledge it to be Divinely inſpir'd.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:179515:16"/>
               <p>Firſt, it muſt be acknowledg'd, that they who deny a Providence, never ſeriouſly conſider'd what God is. The <hi>Idea</hi> which we naturally have of God, inſtructs us, that he is the moſt perfect of all Beings that exiſt, or may exiſt, as already has been ſaid. Now can we believe, that a God, who ſhould neglect his own Works, and ſhould ſhut himſelf up in Heaven, without taking any care of what he has created, can be a perfect Being, ſeeing that among Men themſelves, thoſe perſons have been always look'd upon with the Higheſt contempt who neglect their own Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. Fathers, for example, who never mind their own Children, and thoſe ſlothful Princes, who like <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> abandon the care of their Dominions, and leave their Subjects at liberty to do whatever ſees good in their own Eyes. How can ſuch a ſluggiſh Remiſsneſs, a Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ſo unbecoming an imperfect Creature, be thought to beſeem the moſt perfect of all Beings. At leaſt it cannot be deny'd, but that if God takes no care of his Creatures, there muſt be a Being more perfect then he. But this is that which cannot be ſaid of a God. <hi>Either me muſt deny</hi> (ſays <hi>Cicero,</hi> I. Natur. Deor.) <hi>that there are Gods, or we muſt confeſs, that they act ſomething Great and Noble: Now there is nothing Greater or more Noble then the Conduct of the World. Were it otherwiſe, we ſhould be forc'd to ſay, that there is ſomething Better and more Perfect then the Deity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, it is not to be imagin'd, that a moſt Wife Being has created ſo many Things which we admire, without propoſing to himſelf ſome End or other. If he have made all theſe Things
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179515:16"/>to ſome End, can we believe that he takes no care to ſee whether he have attain'd his End or no, and whether his Creatures do what they ought to do. I know very well what <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſaid, That it would be a defect in the Felicity of God, ſhould he be troubl'd with the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the World: But he was groſly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as having a Falſe <hi>Idea</hi> of Felicity. For true Beatitude conſiſts not in doing nothing, but in doing things both Great and Noble. A Being that is not perfect, cannot be happy in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, more eſpecially, if you ſpeak of a Being Supreamly Wiſe. Now it cannot be imagin'd, that a Being, who neglects the looking after what he has taken pleaſure to create, can be a perfect Being. Therefore there-might be ſome ground for <hi>Epicurus</hi>'s Argument, if God might be thought to tire himſelf with Governing the World. But how can he be weary who does all things by the only Act of his Will, wherein his Almighty Hand, that ne'r was tir'd in building the vaſt Structure, where all Beings are enclos'd, has not the leaſt ſhare of Pains or Trouble.</p>
               <p>But if they who deny Providence, never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what God is, neither did they ever conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the nature of the Creatures. Certain it is, that as they were created out of nothing, they would infallibly return to nothing again, if the ſame hand that form'd 'em, did not ſupport and preſerve 'em; for becauſe they Exiſt at this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, it does not follow that they ſhall Exiſt the next moment. 'Tis requiſite then, that he who preſerv'd 'em the firſt moment, ſhould preſerve 'em ſtill; and this is ſo much the more neceſſary
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179515:17"/>for him to do, becauſe there are a thouſand Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents that might every hour deſtroy 'em, were there not a Supream Being that preſerves 'em. It is not the ſame thing with them, as with God, whoſe Eſſence at the ſame time implies Exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: for we may think of the Being of Creatures, yet not ſuppoſe that they Exiſt. Now if it be true, that the Creatures cannot ſubſiſt without being ſuſtain'd by the ſame Hand that made 'em, we muſt of neceſſity conclude from their ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that there is a Providence.</p>
               <p>We muſt be farther confirm'd in this Opinion, if we conſider the wonderful Order which is obſerv'd in all parts of the Univerſe, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver alters, but has ſubſiſted for ſo many Ages in the midſt of ſo many Changes and Revolutions: The Harmony and Concord of ſo many Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of different Natures; the Regular Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe Great Bodies, that roule Majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally over our Heads: their Changes ſo conſtant, their Conjunctions ſo juſt, their Revolutions ſo well order'd, together with a thouſand things which are our continual wonder, yet, which we can never admire enough. For it is impoſſible to revolve this Order in our Minds, without acknowledging a Providence, unleſs we deſign'd to be as extravagant as He, who, obſerving a State well Govern'd, a Family well manag'd, or an Army under good Conduct and Diſcipline, ſhould deny that State or Kingdom to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by any Magiſtracy, that the Family had any body to look after it, or that the Army had any General or Chieftain to Command it.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:179515:17"/>
               <p>They who deny a Providence extol themſelves in this Particular, very much, and make ſome Objections. If it were true, ſay they, that all things were well regulated, we ſhould believe that God concern'd himſelf with what is acted here below; but we obſerve ſo many diſorders in the World, that we cannot perſuade our ſelves that a Being altogether Wiſe and Omnipotent ſhould govern the Univerſe. Nay, 'twould be much better, add they, to affirm, that he takes no heed of what happens upon Earth, then to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert that he beholds and ſuffers ſo much Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Whence comes it to paſs that Thunder rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles in the Deſarts, that Hail and Thunderbolts fall upon Rocks, and that it Rains upon the Sea? To what purpoſe ſerve Flies, Worms, and other Inſects? Whence comes it to paſs, that Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Vomit forth Fire and Aſhes? Wherefore are we peſter'd with Monſters and Serpents? Were there a Providence, would it not hinder thoſe Inundations, thoſe Earthquakes that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and ſwallow-up whole Cities; thoſe Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences that lay waſte whole Kingdoms, and thoſe Extraordinary Accidents that ſeem to menace the Univerſe with utter Ruin? Or would that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence permit the Oppreſſion of Virtue, and the Triumphs of Vice and Impiety?</p>
               <p>But firſt I would fain know of thoſe who make theſe Objections, whether they are well aſſur'd that what they call Diſorder, be really Diſorder, and what they ſay is badly Manag'd be truly the defect of Government? Did it never ſo fall out that they deceiv'd themſelves, and have they not frequently blam'd the Conduct of Princes, while
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179515:18"/>they were ignorant of the Reaſons, but admir'd it afterwards when they underſtood the Grounds of their Proceedings. What a Raſhneſs is it in Mortal Men, whoſe Underſtandings are confin'd within ſuch Narrow Bounds, to determine ſo poſitively of what they know not in the leaſt, and to believe there is Diſorder in all things, of which they cannot reach the Cauſes? The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of thoſe People to me ſeems no leſs Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant then that of the K. of <hi>Caſtille,</hi> who boaſted that if God had call'd him to his Council, when he fram'd the World, he could have give him better Advice. We know no more, ſays one of the moſt Celebrated Writers of this Age, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of God in the Government of his Creatures, then an Infant, who having been bred up in a Deſart, and all of a ſudden brought into ſome great and Populous City, could be able to underſtand all the Changes that would happen, without Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, before his Eyes. He would many times blame what was by no means to be cenſur'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not underſtand the Reaſon of thoſe Alterations.</p>
               <p>The Cauſe why they ſo badly argue proceeds from this, that they conſider thoſe things which appear to them ſo ill manag'd, diſt junctively from the other Works of God, and for that they do not reflect with ſufficient Attention upon the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency between thoſe things, and others which they know. Wherein they are no leſs ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous then they, who content themſelves with only ſeeing ſome Scenes of a Dramatic Poem, but never examine the Coherence and Unfolding, or rather Winding up of the Whole; or they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179515:18"/>who in Pictures only fix their Eyes upon the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows; orélſe like thoſe, who in a piece of Tapiſtry work, look only upon the looſe Bordering, which for the moſt part preſents the Sight with only monſtrous and imperfect Figures.</p>
               <p>In the Second place, I could wiſh, that they who find ſo many diſorders, and ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion upon the Earth, would tell me, Whether they meet with nothing that is rightly order'd? and, Whether they never obſerv'd any characters of Wiſdom in the Conduct of the World? They would not preſume to aver it. Let 'em then tell me, by what means all thoſe things which appear to Them to be in decent Order, come to be ſo wiſely manag'd? Certainly they muſt, at leaſt in that reſpect, acknowledge that there is a Providence; and as to other Things, they ought to have as much Equity, as a Man of good Senſe, when he judges of a Book, that Treats of vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Subjects, and which is written in ſeveral Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, of which he underſtands but one part. If that which he underſtands pleaſes him, he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to himſelf, that what he underſtands not will be no leſs ſatisfactory to him, could he but dive into the ſence of it. God would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from Men, all the Ends for which he made all things: But ſome he has not unveil'd, on purpoſe to exerciſe and humble their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that they might adore the Impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trable depths of his Wiſdom. We ought to extol him, ſays <hi>St. Auſtin,</hi> as well for what we know to be wonderful in his Works, as for what we cannot penetrate. For that our Life
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179515:19"/>being of ſo ſhort continuance, and we our ſelves confin'd within ſo ſmall a part of Time, and of the Univerſe; 'tis impoſſible that we ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the Order and Deſigns of that Eternal Wiſdom, that views the vaſt immenſity of Time with one ſingle Glance, and with linking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that infinite variety of the Events of this Life, like to many Rings claſp'd one within an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, forms that long Chain of his Providence, that ſhall extend it ſelf to the fartheſt ſucceſſion of all Ages.</p>
               <p>After theſe General Remarks, let us enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the examination of theſe diſorders which they ſpeak of. They wonder, in the firſt place, why Thunder rattles in uninhabited Deſarts, that Hail falls upon Rocks; and why Lightning le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels with the Ground high and large Trees: not minding that theſe are but the Conſequences of the Laws which God has eſtabliſh'd. I am as much to ſeek wherefore they do not likewiſe complain that the Sun ſhines upon, and warms thoſe Deſarts, becauſe the Heat of the Sun ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hales the Vapours and Exhalations which thick'n into thoſe Clouds that generate both Tempeſts and Lightning. They wonder why the Rain which ſerves to fertilize the Earth, falls not more regularly upon only Lands Manur'd, and not upon Highway's; or upon the Sea, which have no need of it. But do they think that Rain has no other Effects, then only to render the Earth fruitful. Do they not know, that the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways would crack and gape through Drouth, were they not moiſten'd by the Rain? And that it is a great Refreſhment to thoſe that Travel in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179515:19"/>hot Countries. <hi>Should it only Rain upon ſown Lands,</hi> ſays that famous Author already cited. <hi>whence ſhould proceed the Springs that are ſo neceſſary to quench our own, and the Thirſt of all Creatures; and how ſhould the Rivers retain that abundance of water which renders 'em Navigable? It Rains upon the Sea: Who ſays that Rain is there unprofitable to temper the ſaltneſs of it, and to make it more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for the nouriſhment of the Fiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They wonder that there ſhould be Mountains cover'd with Snow, and others that vomit forth Fire, that there ſhould be Deſarts and ſteep Rocks. Not conſidering that their variety of Objects it is, which makes the Beauty of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and that God manifeſts his Wiſdom more in that Diverſity, then in a Uniformity, thô grateful to the ſight, yet ſtill the ſame.</p>
               <p>They wonder why there ſhould be Inſects, as if we could ſufficiently admire the Wiſdom of God in thoſe little Animals; for example, in the little Republick of the Bees, which employ'd the Brains of an Ancient Philoſopher, for above Threeſcore years; and which at this day finds work enough for thoſe that dive into the ſecrets of Nature. Should we as diligently enquire into the Uſe of theſe little Inſects, as into the Benefit of Simples, we ſhould doubtleſs diſcover very profitable Secrets, I will not except the very Flies and Gnats, which are ſaid to be uſeful to purifie the Air, in places where there are the greateſt number of 'em, and where they are moſt troubleſome, and give the greateſt annoyance.</p>
               <p>They admire there ſhould be poiſonous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and other venemous Beaſts, but never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179515:20"/>that there are many excellent Remedies extracted out of Serpents; and that Sovereign Antidotes are frequently made of compounded Poiſons that ſerve to eaſe the Pains of Men; and that in general, all theſe things which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves to be either ſuperfluous or hurtful, would afford us matter of Admiration, if we conſider'd 'em as we ought to do, and if we ſhould find that in the General harmony of the Creatures, they produce the ſame Effect as Baſes and Treb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in a lovely Conſort.</p>
               <p>As for Monſters, moſt certain it is, that thoſe petty Miſcarriages and Deviations of Nature ought not to leſſen the eſteem, which it becomes us to have for Nature's Author: for that theſe Monſters no way render the World imperfect. On the contrary, this variety of Creatures, of which ſome are more perfect then others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute not a little to the Beauty of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Monſtrous Animals are leſs perfect then others of their kind, whoſe Proportions are more juſt: but there are a thouſand things which are to be admir'd in the ſtructure of deformed Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which could only be the Handy-work of an Infinite Power. 'Tis with Monſters as with Diſcords in Muſick, where oft-times a Diſcord artfully intermixed with ſeveral Concords, makes the ſweeteſt Harmony. Beſides, theſe Monſters are the Conſequences of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, which is between the Imagination of the Mother, and the Fruits in her Womb; which Communication was moſt wiſely eſtabliſh'd for the forming of the Infant. True it is, that God might have prevented this Communication from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179515:20"/>cauſing any diſorder; but why may we not ſay as well, that it was the pleaſure of God to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſo ſometimes for the puniſhment of Men? Sometimes to ſet a greater value upon the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his other Works; Sometimes for other Reaſons which are in Truth, unknown to us; which nevertheleſs we ought not to find fault with, in regard, that of all thoſe things that fall within our Knowledge, there is not any one that does not afford us ample occaſion to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the infinite Wiſdom of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
               <p>They wonder that there ſhould be Inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Earthquakes, Subterraneal Conflagrations, and other Accidents which ſeem to threaten the World with utter Ruin. But ſo far it is, that they from hence can prove there is not a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that it is rather a proof of the contrary. For I beſeech ye, were there not a Providence, how is it poſſible that the World ſhould ſubſiſt in the midſt of ſuch violent Concuſſions, or that it ſhould have held out ſo long time? A Ship abandon'd to the Mercy of the Winds, without either Helm or Pilot can never run a ſteady courſe, without daſhing againſt the Rocks, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwallow'd up by the Waves.</p>
               <p>Whence comes it then, that theſe ſubterraneal Fires, theſe Earthquakes, and theſe Inundations cauſe not that univerſal Havock which they might do? By what unexpected Power are the Effects of theſe dreadful Accidents, ſuſpended or limited? Who is it that corrects the diſtempers of a corrupted Air? What Virtue purifies whole Cities and Regions infected with the Peſtilence?
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179515:21"/>Certainly he muſt be very blind, who ſees not that 'tis the ſame hand which made the Univerſe that preſerves it; and that after God has made uſe of theſe Unundations, theſe Fires and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes for thoſe ends, which to us are for the moſt part unknown, he ſtops 'em from going any farther, and deſtroying the vaſt Machine of the World.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they are aſtoniſh'd, that Good Men ſhould be ſo often oppreſt, and that the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhould Triumph; That Impiety and Vice ſhould Reign predominant, and that Innocence and Virtue ſhould be overwhelmed. This is one of their great Objections, that has ſo much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd the Wiſe in all Ages. <hi>Claudian</hi> confeſſes ingenuouſly, <hi>That he queſtions whether the World be Governed by a Wiſe, Intelligent Providence, or by Blind Fortune, beholding Virtue under Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and</hi> Rufinus <hi>the moſt famous Criminal of his Age, flouriſhing in High Advancement.</hi> And it is reported of a certain Philoſopher, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an Atheiſt, becauſe he obſerv'd, that God did not inflict immediate Puniſhment upon a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd Perſon. And the Wiſe <hi>Cato,</hi> unfortunate in fighting for the Liberty of his Country, could not forbear ſaying, <hi>That there was a great Incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in the Government of the Gods.</hi> To which I may add what is related of <hi>Domocritus, That he put out his I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yes with the Reverberation of a Glittering Buckler, becauſe he would not behold the Proſperity of the Wicked.</hi> Thô I muſt confeſs, that this laſt Story ſeems to me very improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For what likely hood is there that <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus,</hi> who only made it his Buſineſs to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179515:21"/>all the World, ſhould be troubl'd at the Proſperity of the Ungodly?</p>
               <p>Now, tho' this Objection ſeems very plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nevertheleſs it is very eaſily anſwered. Firſt it is not always true, that Virtue is oppreſs'd, and Vice recompenc'd. Good Men are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was Afflicted, and the Wicked are frequently puniſh'd; No Man will preſume to deny it. Nor are there any Ages or Years that do not furniſh us with Examples. Thus the ſame <hi>Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> who was offended at the Proſperity of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finus,</hi> ſays, That the Puniſhment which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, abſolv'd the Gods, <hi>Abſtulit hunc tandem Rufini Paena Tumultum, Abſolvit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deos.</hi> In the Second Place, People who are not ſo, are many times thought to be Virtuous and Good People, becauſe they carry a fair Outſide of Probity and Piety. 'Tis needleſs to produce any Proofs of it; 'tis agreed upon by all the World; there is no Perſon that has not been frequently deceiv'd; and there are an Infinite number who deceive themſelves.</p>
               <p>But to unfold this difficulty more clearly, I aſſert, that they moſt groſly deceive themſelves, when they imagine the Wicked to be happy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they appear to be ſo; becauſe they are Rich; becauſe they are advanced to vaſt prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and wallow in pleaſure and delights. How many are there that ſeem to enjoy a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Felicity, who are really moſt unfortunate, and tormented with bitter Pangs of an accuſing Conſcience? How many wealthy People are there, whoſe Condition is much more ſad then that of the moſt Miſerable Wretches? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179515:22"/>great Men are there, who in their Elevated Stations enjoy no reſt or quiet Day or Night? I need no other Teſtimony then <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who could not forbear declaring to the Roman Senate, that every Day he dy'd a Cruel Death. <hi>Could you but look into the Inſides of thoſe that you eſteem Happy and Rich,</hi> ſaid <hi>Seneca, you would find 'em to be Miſerable, to be Poor, to be Infamous, and that they reſemble thoſe Walls which are only Painted without ſide. Such a Felicity is no ſolid and true Felicity; 'tis only an Image and ſlight Appearance of it. For which reaſon it is, that while they can ſtand upon their Legs, and make a vain Bravado of Grandeur, they appear what they are not, and make People believe 'em happy. But if any accident befals 'em, that puts 'em out of Order, and diſcovers 'em, then you come to ſee the Filth and Infamy that bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd Splendour conceals.</hi> And the Famous Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>Tacitus,</hi> ſpeaking of Tyrants, <hi>could we but ſee their Souls laid open,</hi> ſays He, <hi>we ſhould behold 'em torn and mangl'd by their own Crimes, like the Bodies of Criminals cut with the Laſhes of the Whip.</hi> We muſt not wonder then to ſee the Wicked Potent and Rich, in Grandeur and Reputation; ſo far from thence concluding that there is no Providence, that we have no reaſon to envy their Felicity.</p>
               <p>I confeſs however, that there would be ſome reaſon to be aſtoniſh'd at their appearing Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, were there no other Life but this, and that we were not then to come to Judgment. But before we blame the Conduct of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or before we deny a Providence, we ought to be aſſur'd there is no other Life to be expected
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179515:22"/>after this, and that God will never puniſh thoſe whom he now ſupports. Now I know not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any one to be met with who will preſume to aſſert, that he is clearly convinced, that there is nothing to be thought of after this Life, that there is nothing to be hop'd or fear'd after Death, tho' there are ſeveral who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to perſuade themſelves, that it is certainly true, with whom we ſhall enter the Liſts in the ſequel of our Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The Second Reflection is, That 'tis an Error to believe good Men Unhappy becauſe they are afflicted; ſeeing that Afflictions are ſo uſeful to thoſe that are expos'd to 'em, whereby to make 'em ſenſible of the Emptineſs of this World, and the Vanities of it; to wean 'em from this Earth, and make 'em think of a better Life; to tame their Pride; to reduce 'em from their Deviations and Wandrings, and bring 'em back to their Duty. Theſe are the Benefits of Misfor-fortune, of which it would be eaſie to convince the moſt obſtinate.</p>
               <p>Now for a Man to be convinc'd, that Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do not render the Sufferers unhappy, he needs no more, but to conſider the Tranquility of mind which Good Men enjoy when they are moſt Afflicted. One would think ſometimes that he ſuffers in the Body of another perſon, or that he is Inſenſible; or if it happen that through the Violence of his Pain, he diſcovers ſome Motions of Impatience, and lets fall ſome Murmurings, he recovers himſelf preſently again. You ſhall ſee Sereneneſs and Joy reſeated in his Countenence: You ſhall hear him bleſs God for Chaſtizing him
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179515:23"/>ſo much Lenity; He acknowledges the Benefit of his Afflictions, and that he ſtood in need of ſuch Paternal Correction.</p>
               <p>If they, againſt whom I diſpute, did but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Divinity of the Scriptures, I could draw from thence an Infinite number of Proofs againſt 'em; but I ſhall content my ſelf with ſending 'em to the School of a Pagan, I mean <hi>Seneca,</hi> who has Compos'd a Treatiſe upon this Subject <hi>Why ſo many Calamities befall good Men?</hi> And thus he argues;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>When you ſee Good Men, and ſuch as are acceptable to the Gods, in Pain, in Trouble, in Adverſity, Travelling through a difficult and Rugged Road; but on the contrary, behold the Wicked in Joy, in Plenty, in Pleaſure, take notice that we are pleas'd with the Modeſty of our Children, and the Liberty of our Servants, that we keep the firſt under ſevere Diſcipline and that we ſometimes bear with the boldneſs of the other. You ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the ſame thing of the Gods. They do not nurture Good Men in Pleaſures and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; they try 'em, they harden 'em, they Train 'em up and Inſtruct 'em like Soldiers which they intend to liſt under their Banners.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe it might be objected againſt him, <q>Is it then advantageous to be Baniſh'd, to be reduc'd to Poverty, to behold the Death of Children, and a dearly beloved Wife, to be branded with Infamy, to ſee a Man's ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft of every thing;</q> He anſwers; <q>"If you wonder that this ſhould be advantageous to any Body, you may as well admire that ſome
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179515:23"/>People are Cur'd by Cutting and Burning, and that Hunger and Drouth are made uſe of to the ſame Effect: But if you conſider with your ſelf, that ſometimes for Healths-ſake the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon is forced to rifle the Veins, to ſcrape and pluck away the Bones, and cut off Members which elſe would endanger the whole Body: You may as well permit us to tell ye, that there are Calamities no leſs advantageous to thoſe that endure 'em.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome will ſay, if there be a Providence, how comes it to paſs that Sin is permitted? This is very near the ſame Argument, which a Pagan Philoſopher made uſe of, <hi>If there be a God,</hi> ſaid He, <hi>whence proceeds Evil?</hi> But he as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly recollects himſelf, <hi>If there be no God whence proceeds Good?</hi> This Difficulty gave the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeans an Occaſion to ſet up two Principles, the one of Good, the other of Evil; and <hi>Manes</hi> borrow'd this Opinion from the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all their Bleſſings to their God <hi>Oromaſdes,</hi> and all their Evils to <hi>Arimanius;</hi> as the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans made <hi>Typhon</hi> the Author of all their Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, while they look'd upon <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris</hi> as the two Deities from which they received all their Kindneſſes. I confeſs, we know not the Reaſon why God permits Sin; yet all that can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from thence, is only this, that ſtill we know not the Deſigns of God; but this Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ought not to make us deny a Truth which we may clearly apprehend, and which is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the ſame Idea that we have of a moſt perfect Being. This is merely want of the force of Wit, and to abandon Evident Truths, for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179515:24"/>ſome Objections that are made us, which we cannot reſolve, tho' the ſame Objections have no other Ground, then the Ignorance and Weakneſs of Human Underſtanding: So that thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who are call'd ſoaring <hi>Wits,</hi> are indeed but pettie Wits, that have more of Pride in 'em then of Senfe and Reaſon,</p>
               <p>What! muſt we preſently deny a Providence, becauſe we are Ignorant of the Conduct of it? If there be a Providence, they Cry, there would be no Diſorder; but if there be no Providence, there would be no Confuſion. Certainly, altho' we could never yet diſcover, why God was pleas'd to permit Sin to enter into the World, yet we ought to believe that he has done it for Reaſons becoming almoſt perfect Being. More eſpecially ſince Sin has given us an Opportunity to diſcover all the Properties of God, his Juſtice, his Holineſs, his Mercy, his Power, his Wiſdom, not to ſpeak of the Admirable Work of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, wherein all the Virtues of a Deity have appeared with ſo much Luſtre; but which God had never thought of, had there been no Sin.</p>
               <p>Certain it is then, that there is a Providence; and this is that which it behov'd us to prove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt Order of our <hi>Indifferent Men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:179515:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Againſt thoſe who believe, that Providence does not concern it ſelf in Affairs of Religion.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome who dare not abſolutely deny that there is a Providence; but they believe that it only concerns it ſelf in things of Higheſt Importance, as Kingdoms, Empires, or Republicks, but never examines what Belief the Inhabitants of the World profeſs, as if it were indifferent to it what Men profeſs'd.</p>
               <p>'Twill be no difficult thing to refute this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. For firſt, 'tis an Error to believe that Providence has not the ſame ſhare in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Little as of Great Affairs. For why ſhould we not believe, that God both Manages and Governs all that he preſerves, and whatever he has made? Is it becauſe it is beneath a God to take care of the ſmalleſt Inſects? But why ſhould that be ſo, when he has been pleas'd to produce 'em out of Nothing? Have we not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon to admire a Sovereign Being, who having all Creatures within the Extent of his Empire, cauſes 'em to ſubſiſt by his Word, and ſuſtains 'em by his Power? Think they that God would debaſe himſelf too much in doing it? But if the Sun ſhines upon the moſt Contemptible Dunghils, yet cannot be ſaid to diſgrace himſelf, why will they not admit that God ſhould act upon the meaneſt of his Creatures, without any diminution of his Grandeur and Majeſty.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:179515:25"/>
               <p>But they will ſay, That 'tis impoſſible that God ſhould manage and govern all things; as if they could be ignorant that the Knowledge and Power of God are Infinite, and that if it be his will alone, there needs no more for him to do in the Ruling and Ordering of all things. And therefore, the Reaſon why our Indifferents argue ſo ill is this, becauſe they have no other Idea of God then of a Man, whoſe illuminations are nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly confin'd, whoſe ſtrength is but very ſmall, and who not being able to buſie himſelf every where, is conſtrain'd to employ himſelf upon a certain Number of Objects.</p>
               <p>Moreover, they imagine, that becauſe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all thoſe little things that are of no uſe to us, 'tis the ſame thing with God; never conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that if God took no care but only of thoſe Creatures that are uſeful to him, or of thoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that bear ſome Proportion with him, all the Creatures, ev'n thoſe only which we moſt eſteem, not being able to add to or diminiſh any thing from his Glory and Felicity; and being all infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely below him, he might equally diſdain and neglect 'em all together.</p>
               <p>But not to enter any farther into the Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Queſtion, muſt not they be willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blind, who dare preſume to number what concerns the Worſhip which is due to the Deity, among things of little Importance? Is there any one which is of greater Moment, then that which has a regard to the Sovereign Being, which all Men ought to adore? And is it likely that God ſhould Rule and Govern Monarchies and Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and leave Men at their Liberty to ſerve
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179515:25"/>him according to their Fancies? As if it were a thing Indifferent to Him, to be ador'd, for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, under the ſhape of the moſt Vile and worthleſs Animals, as the Pagans painted ſome of their Gods. Is it poſſible that Men can have ſuch extravagant thoughts of the moſt perfect of all Beings? Where is that King ſo Negligent as to permit his Subjects the Liberty to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own humours in his Affairs, in his Armies, in his Exchequer, and leaves it to their Diſcretion to Obey and Serve him as their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricio's lead 'em? How then can they who boaſt their Wit preſume to ſay of God, the Wiſeſt of all Beings, what no Man would adventure to ſay of a Perſon meerly Mortal?</p>
               <p>Beſides, were it true, that God took no care of things that concern Religion, whence comes it to paſs, that they who are of this Opinion pay ſome certain Homage to the Deity? Wherefore do they ſometimes pray to him, ſince God takes no notice of what they do, and conſequently never troubles himſelf about their neglect of his Worſhip? Their Actions ill agree with their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and cauſe thoſe that ſee 'em to believe that they are of another Opinion. Therefore it was a good ſaying of one <hi>Diocles,</hi> who eſpying <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> in the Temple, cry'd out, <hi>What a Feaſt, what a Spectacle is this for me, to ſee</hi> Epicurus <hi>in the Temple? All my Suſpicions are Vaniſh'd, Piety re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſumes her Seat, and I never more clearly beheld the Grandeur of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>then now, that I ſee</hi> Epicurus <hi>upon his Knees.</hi> Certainly, if this Opinion, which we have refuted were true, there would be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any more need of paying Worſhip to a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179515:26"/>'Twas true, that <hi>Epicurus</hi> confeſs'd, that the Excellency of Divine Nature deſerv'd of it ſelf, that ſome Honour ſhould be given to Her, tho' ſhe concern'd her ſelf no more with the World, then if there were no ſhare of her in it, and tho' there were nothing to be expected by it from Her. But he only ſpoke thus in conformity to the Common Sentiments. For, in ſhort, the God of that Phyloſopher, according to his Syſtem, was a Piece apart from the Workmanſhip, which a Man might well ſuppoſe not to belong to it, and yet no change befall it. Otherwiſe it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that if he had acted and ſpoken conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to his Real Opinions, he would have ſaid in plain Terms, that Piety was a fruitleſs thing, and he would never have perform'd any act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. <hi>Cicero</hi> therefore rightly underſtood him, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Nat. Deor. There are ſome People,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and have been, before now, who believe that the Gods never meddle with human Affairs. But if that Opinion be true, what will become of Piety?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Immortality of the Soul.</head>
               <p>I Come to thoſe who never much torment themſelves, whither there be any Providence or no, becauſe they hold the Soul to be Mortal, that it periſhes with the Body, or at leaſt, that there is no farther fear of any thing after this Life; that there will be no Judgment; that all that has been ſaid of Paradiſe and Hell
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179515:26"/>are meer Fables, ſuch as the Pagan feign'd of their <hi>Eliſian</hi> Fields, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore that all Religions ought to be indifferent to Us; ſince we ſhall be never the more Happy, nor the more Unfortunate, whatever Religion we Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace.</p>
               <p>'Tis a wonderful thing, that there ſhould be found among Chriſtians, Men that dare deny what the Heathens have acknowledg'd, and what the moſt Barbarous of Nations acknowledge to this Day, as we are given to underſtand by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Relations. And this to ſuch a degree, that far from believing that the Soul periſhes, they have rather choſen to hold, ſome of 'em, that the Soul was from all Eternity. Others, that when the Soul took leave of one Body it tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migrated into another, or elſe was re-united to God; or that it was transform'd into ſome Angel or Devil; or that it intermix'd it ſelf with the Elements. And this Opinion of the Soul's being Immortal, infuſed that Courage and Undauntedneſs into 'em, which they made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Fight, as <hi>Bartholinus</hi> obſerves of the <hi>Danes,</hi> in his Book of the Antiquity of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis a thing ſo much the more ſurprizing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are an Infinite Number of Reaſons that convince us of the Immortality of the Soul. I might prove it by the ardent Deſires of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and by that Idea which we naturally have of a future Life; an Idea which nothing can Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate: So that there is no perſon who indepent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from all Conſideration, and from all Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but either fears or hopes ſomething, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he has either led a Virtuous or Vicious
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179515:27"/>Life, when he ponders upon that ſame darkſom and gloomy Futurity, wherein the Preſent Life ſets from our Eyes. But to make out this Truth as clear as day, I argue thus. If the Soul dy'd, ſuch a Death would happen, either becauſe the parts of it would come to ſeparate, or becauſe it would deſtroy it ſelf; or becauſe ſome other created Subſtance would deſtroy it, or becauſe that God himſelf would annihilate it. There can be conceiv'd no other Cauſes of the Soul's dying. But it is certain, that there can nothing like this be ſaid of our Soul.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It cannot be ſaid, that the Parts of the Soul ſeparate from one another; becauſe the Soul has no parts. It is a Spirit. And he muſt be blind that dares deny it, and aſſert, that the Soul is no more then Matter, then Wind, or a Vapour, then a Certain Agitation of ſubtil Spirits intermix'd with the Blood. It is impoſſible to conceive, that a Soul which knows it ſelf, and all other Beings that ſurround it, that reaches ſublime Truths, that knows an Inviſible God, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects with it ſelf upon its own thoughts, that meaſures the Stars, the Earlh, and Seas, that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects our Senſes and Imagination; that pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates into Futurity, and diſcovers the deepeſt Secrets, ſhould be nothing but anagitated Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; becauſe that nothing is more incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible then a Body that thinks, that reaſons, that deliberates and reflects upon it ſelf. Which way ſoever the Parts of a Body are chang'd, it can never be brought to that paſs by thoſe various Changes or Rangings, that if it knew not it ſelf before, it ſhould ever come to know it ſelf; nor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179515:27"/>could it ever be made capable of having one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle thought. With all the Efforts of our Wit, we can never comprehend what <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſaid, That our Reaſonings and our Idea's are no more then the Agitation of certain Little Bodies, and that the Circular Motion of an Atome, may be the Vaſt and Immenſe Idea of Infinity. It is alſo as abſurd to ſay that a Body knows, as to ſay that a thought is Red or Green; that the Act of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing is Hot or Cold, or that a Metaphiſical Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation is round or ſquare. 'Tis clear then, that the Soul is not Material, and that by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it has no parts; and therefore it cannot dye. No Sickneſs can deſtroy it, becauſe it has no blood, nor humour that can feed it. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sword, nor Fire can kill it, becauſe it has no parts that Iron can divide, or Fire conſume.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Neither can the Soul be ſaid to deſtroy it ſelf; for Right Reaſon teaches us, that nothing tends of it ſelf to its own Deſtruction and Ruin; that every Being is deſirous of it ſelf to remain in the ſame Condition wherein it is; and that every Change that happens to any ſubject pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from an Exterior Cauſe; beſides, that it can never be conceiv'd how a Soul ſhould deſtroy it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It cannot be ſaid, that the Soul can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>troy'd by other Created Subſtances; becauſe we ought not to aſſure our ſelves of what we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annot conceive, unleſs God reveals it to us Now it is impoſſible to comprehend that a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed and finite Subſtance, can deſtroy a Spiritual Nature; nor do we know it to be otherwiſe by Revelation.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:179515:28"/>
               <p n="4">4. It cannot be ſaid, that God deſtroys and annihilates our Souls. For beſides that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilation of a Being, is one of thoſe things of which there is not any example in Nature; we have no Revelation that God deſigns the Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation of Souls. On the contrary, if they with whom we contend, would acknowledge the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Scripture, it would be eaſie for me to produce 'em proofs, which invincibly make out this immortality which we aſſert.</p>
               <p>This Firſt Argument may be ſupported by a Second, which is this, That if the Soul be not immortal, and that there be no other Life after this, we muſt then conclude, that it was only given to Man to render him more miſerable then the Beaſts, and to be a torment to him. For if Man had not a Rational Soul, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of what is paſs'd, the Conſideration of the Preſent, and the Apprehenſion of Futurity would never afflict his Mind; but he would be like the Beaſts, which if we may believe the new Philoſophers, feel no pain, or, if they do feel any, 'tis only a preſent pain. If then the Soul be not immortal, it would have been better that God had made us walking Machines, then to give us a Soul only to make us Suffer.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſaid, that Man being ſo like to Beaſts, all dies with him, as it is with other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. But this Objection is unworthy a Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Man. 'Tis true, that there is ſome Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity between a Man and a Beaſt. A Man is Born and is ſubject to Death; he preſerves his Life by nouriſhment, and his Kind by Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and he is ſubject to the irregularities of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179515:28"/>All this is common with the Beaſts. I confeſs likewiſe that there is a Conformity which is diſgraceful to Man; and this is that which conſiſts in the diſorders of the Body and Sences, and the Predominancy of the Paſſions. 'Tis a ſhame to Man, that his Paſſions over-rule him, where Reaſon ought to Command, and that he is not the Maſter of his own Body, nor of all the Motions of it. Nevertheleſs, all that can be concluded from hence, is, that Man is Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſo far as he has any thing of Conformity with Beaſts. But we muſt renounce our Reaſon, if we deny that Man has not an infinite number of things that exalt him above Brutes; and in that reſpect it is, that Man is Immortal.</p>
               <p>Althô they who believe the Soul to be Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, laugh at the Revelation, yet there are ſome who make uſe of a Paſſage in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their Opinion. 'Tis in the <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.19, 20, 21. <hi>The ſame thing befalls both Man and Beaſts, the death of the One is like the death of the other, both the one and the other breathe the ſame Breath, and Man has no advantage above a Beaſt; for all is vanity; All goes the ſame way; All was duſt and to duſt they ſhall return. Who knows whether the breath of Man mounts upward, or whether the breath of a Beaſt deſcends downward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if theſe People who borrow the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſupport their Error, had read the Book from which they-fetcht their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they would have ſeen that that ſame Great and Wiſe Prince was far from believing the Soul to be Mortal. His aim is there, only to withdraw the hearts of Men from the Love of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179515:29"/>the World, from their extraordinary Propenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Creatures, and all things that fall under the Senſes. On purpoſe to incline and perſuade 'em to Love, to Fear, and Serve the Lord only. And this is the concluſion which he draws at the end of his Book from all the Arguments which he produc'd before. The ſcope of the whole Diſcourſe is, <hi>Fear God and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for this is the whole Duty of Man.</hi> Now I leave it to Judgment, Whether if <hi>Salomon</hi> had thought that the Soul did not ſubſiſt after death, he would have taken ſo much pains, to excite Men to the exerciſes of Piety, for which there was no reward to be expected, ſince the Belief of the Immortality of the Soul, is the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Piety and Religion.</p>
               <p>But for an abſolute Conviction, that this Great King did not believe the Soul to be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, there needs no more then to read his Tenth Chapter. From the very beginning he threatens Men with a Judgment to come, and exhorts 'em to remember God in the days of their youth, and not to delay their Turning to God till<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the laſt years of their Lives. A needleſs Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation if the Soul were to dye. For what reaſon is there that Man ſhould fear any thing after death, if All were to dye with him. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the 9th Verſe he tells us in expreſs terms, <hi>That the duſt returns to the earth from whence it was taken, but that the Spirit returns to God that gave it.</hi> Is not this an invincible Proof that he believed the Immortality of our Souls. For how could it be ſaid, that our Spirit ſhould return to God that gave it; if it ſubſiſted no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:179515:29"/>after it was departed from the Body which it enlivened. Is it poſſible that a nothing of Soul and Spirit ſhould return to the Boſom of God?</p>
               <p>The wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> ſo little believ'd our Soul to be Mortal, that in the ſame Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. he ſays, <hi>God ſhall judge the Juſt and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt; and then ſhall be the time for all things, and over all his Works.</hi> which he would never have ſaid, had he had the leaſt Thought that our Soul di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Body.</p>
               <p>So that by the Paſſage which they alledge, he meant no other thing, but that in reſpect of the Body, the condition of the Beaſts was equal to that of Men, that the ſame thing befals him, and that to judge by outward appearances, when we ſee a Man dye, it ſeems as if he dy'd like a Beaſt; and that there was no difference between 'em. And this was the Judgment which the Prophane Libertines in <hi>Salomon</hi>'s time made of it.</p>
               <p>But what we have ſaid, is certainly the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſence of the words. For if from the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, Who knows whether the breath of a Beaſt aſcends upward, and the breath of a Beaſt deſcends downward?</hi> We muſt conclude that if <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> was ignorant of that which was to happen, he would have ſpoken againſt his own knowledge, ſeeing that in the 12th Chapter he ſays expreſly, <hi>That the Spirit returns to God.</hi> We muſt alſo believe, that he queſtions whether or no the Breath of Beaſts deſcended downward, ſince he makes uſe of the ſame Expreſſion, who knows whether the Breath of a Beaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now is this a thing that ſo wiſe a Man as <hi>Salomon</hi> could doubt of, or could he be inclin'd to obſerve an Error which few believe,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179515:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>that the Spirit of Beaſts is immortal? Thô we muſt confeſs there are ſome people that are of this Opinion, if we may believe the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Relation of the Eaſtern <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It will be ſaid, perhaps, that the Soul being ſtrictly united with the Body, it cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd how the Body ſhould dye, and the Soul be Immortal. But this Argument is abſurd: for were the Soul and Body of the ſame Nature, there were ſome room for this Objection. But in regard they are of a different Nature, and that the motions of the Soul are abſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent from thoſe of the Body; As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when ſhe meditates upon God; Why may we not ſay, that it ſubſiſts without a Body like the Angels? And ſo much for this ſubject; Let us now examine whether we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a day of Judgment?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Judgment to come.</head>
               <p>IT is impoſſible to reflect upon the Nature of God, without being convinc'd of a Day of Judgment. The <hi>Idea</hi> which we have of God, obliges him to look upon him as a Being Supreamly Wiſe, moſt Juſt, moſt Holy, and moſt Perfect, But we can never conſider him as a Being moſt Wiſe, Juſt, and Perfect, unleſs we underſtand at the ſame time, that he is one day to call Men to Judgment, and to reward or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh 'em, according as they have lived upon the Earth. In ſhort, How can it be conceiv'd, that a God who made all things, who loves Order
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:179515:30"/>and Holineſs to the higheſt Degree, and who always acts conformably to his Virtues, can let go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſh'd the Contempts which his Creatures put upon his Laws, and that he can look with the ſame Glances of his favour upon thoſe that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves in his Praiſes, and they that Vomit forth Blaſphemies againſt him; thoſe that confeſs his Holy Name, and thoſe that abjure it; upon Virtuous Men, and the moſt Infamous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchees; upon St. <hi>Peter</hi> and a <hi>Herod;</hi> upon St. <hi>Paul</hi> and a <hi>Nero;</hi> a St. <hi>John</hi> and a <hi>Domitian;</hi> and yet this is that which we muſt ſay of God, were it true that there would be no Day of Judgment. For that Perſon muſt be very Ignorant of the Affairs and Tranſactions of this World, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands not, that Puniſhment does not always attend the Tranſgreſſion, and that the Wicked are not always Chaſtiz'd; but that the Innocent are ſometimes oppreſs'd, and the Guilty juſtify'd.</p>
               <p>Now can we believe, that the Sanctity and Wiſdom of God would ſuffer Virtue to remain without Reward, or Vice without Puniſhment, had he not decreed a Day wherein to render unto every Man according to his Works? No, doubtleſs, God has not ſuffer'd the Wicked all to go Unpuniſh'd, that Men might not believe there was no Providence; nor does he puniſh all, that Men might thence infer, there will be a time of Judgment. The Inviſible Hand of God collects together whatever Man does, whatever he thinks, and whatever he ſays; all is hoarded up in the Treaſure of his Juſtice. But after God has ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd all his Magazine, he will return all back
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:179515:31"/>again, and cauſe to Re-deſcend on Men, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Men ſent up to Heaven.</p>
               <p>To this firſt Argument, in my Opinion, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be added, which is taken from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, the Troubles, and the Agitations of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when a Man has committed any Crimes, tho' ſecret Tranſgreſſions, and ſuch are not to be diſcover'd. For from whence proceed thoſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, I beſeech ye, if it be not from an Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a Judgment, which there is no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of avoiding?</p>
               <p>It may be objected perhaps, that there are none but the weaker ſort that labour under theſe Diſquiets, theſe Turmoils and ſtings of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; little Children, poor Ideots, and ſilly Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But where is that Man, who having ſworn a falſe Oath, committed a Murder, or any other Crying Act of Injuſtice, is not ſenſible of the ſharpe Rebukes and Upbraidings of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? 'Tis not what Women only or Children do; this is a queſtion reaches all that have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended againſt Heaven.</p>
               <p>It may be alſo farther ſaid, that 'tis the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the Rigour of Human Laws which cauſes all thoſe Terrors, not the Dread of any Caeleſtial Tribunal. But whence then comes it to paſs, that thoſe Monarchs, who ſet themſelves above the Reach of all Terreſtial Juſtice, and boaſted of their Abominations, were not exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from theſe Affrights and Convulſions of ſelf-Conviction; ſuch as <hi>Nero, Tiberius, Caligula Caracalla,</hi> who were flattered every day, that they might do what they pleas'd, and who never heard
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:179515:31"/>a word of the Law of God, of the Severity of his Juſtice, or of a Judgment to come?</p>
               <p>Others will alledge, that theſe Commotions are the Effect of our Education. But how comes it, that we neglect and contemn ſo many other things infus'd into us by our Education, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can deface theſe deep Impreſſions? Whence proceeds it, that all Mankind, with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd Efforts, could never calm theſe Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Agitations, nor diſſipate theſe Fears? Whence comes it to paſs, that upon th' approach of Death, the Greateſt Libertines, and moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, tremble at the remembrance of their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and their Horrors ſtill augment, the nearer they draw toward their end? For, if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing were to follow but Annihilation, whence ſo much Agony.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it will be ſaid, that there are many People who feel none of theſe Inward Stings. But beſides that, it would be a difficult thing to name any of thoſe Perſons whoſe Conſciences are altogether dead and Inſenſible; and that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might be thought to be void of all Fear, becauſe they knew how to conceal it; their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Number can by no means weak'n our Argument; as it does not follow that the Exiſtence of God is not a Truth beyond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, becauſe there are ſome perhaps that do not believe it.</p>
               <p>The Univerſal Conſent, in reference to this Point, of all Nations that have acknowledg'd a Deity, is a ſufficiently convincing Proof of the Truth of what we poſitively aſſert. For how comes it, that ſo many Men agree in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179515:32"/>altho' they differ in ſo many other Things? Is it not a Proof that this is one of thoſe Truths of which we come to the knowledge as ſoon as we begin to make uſe of our Reaſon, and which we cannot withſtand without renouncing the Light of our Intellects? It would be no difficult Thing for me to prove this Univerſal Conſent, would I but collect together what the Pagans have written concerning the condition of Souls after Death; of the Judges before whom they were to appear; of the Puniſhments and Rewards prepar'd for Men in the other World; all that <hi>Plato</hi> believ'd upon this Subject; and Particularly the<note place="margin">Plat. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. l. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> Recital which he cauſes one <hi>Amnenius</hi> to make in his Republic, whom he introduces return'd to Earth twelve Days after his Death, to make a Report of all that is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in Hell, and giving an Account, that the Judges, before whom the Souls of the Departed appear, place the Juſt upon the Right hand, and the Wicked upon the Left, and cauſe the Virtuous to aſcend to Heaven, while the Latter are forced to deſcend.</p>
               <p>I might add what <hi>Strabo</hi> relates of the <hi>Brach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> among the Indians; what is recited to us by thoſe who have Travell'd into <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America.</hi> And I might add to all theſe Proofs, another, which might be drawn from the Opinion of almoſt all Nations, that there was a neceſſary Duty incumbent upon 'em to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peaſe the Deity; which prevail'd ſo far, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many offer'd Human Sacrifices for that pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:179515:32"/>
               <p>I add to all theſe Arguments this Reflection, That if there be no future Judgment, Virtue is no more then a Fantom, and that 'tis a Folly to purſue her Maxims: Men may give themſelves over to all ſorts of Crimes and Impieties, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reluctancy; he may be a Traytor, Perjur'd Wretch, a Knave, a Faithleſs Villain, an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer; from this time forward he has no more to do but to make himſelf moſt powerful in Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and preſerve his Life, ſince he has nothing to fear after Death, no more then if he had led a Life the moſt Exact and Virtuous that could be imagin'd. But where is that Man to be found that wou'd not abominate an Opinion, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, in this manner, the moſt Horrid of Crimes, and moſt Impious Enormities? Or if it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, what Man would be willing to brook that the World ſhould be no other then a wide Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle of only Thieves and Robbers, a meer Chaos, where there was no Curb upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Where it is prov'd, that altho' we had no certain Proofs of a Judgment to come, yet we ought to live in ſuch a manner, as if we were aſſur'd of one.</head>
               <p>LET us preſs a little cloſer upon thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom we diſpute, and put the Queſtion to 'em, whether they are well aſſur'd, that all that is ſaid of the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179515:33"/>and Life to come, are Fables and Stories, as they loudly gave out. Do they believe it to be a thing contrary to the Virtue of a moſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Being, to puniſh thoſe who have ſo often Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated his Laws, thoſe that refus'd to obey him, and whom he ſpar'd in this Life? Is it leſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming God to be Juſt then to be Merciful? I queſtion whether any Body will preſume to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, tho' there are many who have doubted the Truth of the Day of Judgment; and others, who upon their Death-beds have ſaid, That they were going to be inform'd of three Things; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were a God? whether the Soul were Immortal? and whether there were a Heaven or Hell? a very Edifying Confeſſion. I will grant that our <hi>Indifferent-Men</hi> may not be abſolutely convinc'd by our alledg'd Reaſons, or by any others which we could produce; However, they muſt confeſs, that there is ſome cauſe to Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether the Sentiment which they have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd be true or no. They believe, that all Remorſe of Conſcience proceeds from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of Education. But I believe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from an Apprehenſion of being puniſh'd for what we have committed, and from the fear of a Judgment, which is not poſſible for us to avoid. They ſay, that I am deceiv'd; yet they ought at leaſt to acknowledge, that it is not ſo clear that I am in an Error; but that there may be ſome reaſon to doubt whether I am or no. This then appears to be their Condition, that they know not certainly, according to their own Confeſſion, whether they ſhall be Eternally Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, as it is requiſite for 'em to acknowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:179515:33"/>that they have deſerv'd to be by their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, or whether they ſhall be annihilated. Good God! What an Uncertainty is this! Would it not then be better, in the midſt of this uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, to practiſe that which would gain 'em Eternal Felicity, if it be true that there is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, then to do thoſe things that are reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Eternal Pains, if there be a Judgment, or a Hell? In the choice of Opinions, which Men know not certainly whether they be true or falſe, ſound Judgment and right Reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that Men ſhould prefer that Steerage that leads 'em to gain, if truth be on their ſide, and where there is nothing to loſe, if they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; and on the other hand, reject that by which they can gain nothing, tho' they were in the Right, but much to loſe, ſhould it prove their Misfortune to be deluded. This is now our Caſe. A Man who lives as if he were to be judg'd, has nothing to be afraid of, ſuppoſing he ſhould be deceiv'd, but every thing to hope for, if he be not in an Error. He has nothing to be afraid of, if he has been miſtaken, unleſs it be, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death he finds no God, no Paradiſe, nor meets any more with himſelf again. I confeſs, that this is to be look'd upon as a great Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; but at leaſt he ought no more to be afraid of any ſuffering, or that he ſhall be more Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then he who has liv'd, as if there were no Judgment to be expected. Both the one and the other muſt loſe their Being, and all the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of Being, as Pain, Pleaſure, Felicity, and Miſery. This is the greateſt Miſchief that can befall a Good Chriſtian, ſuppoſing him to be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179515:34"/>in an Error. But if he be not deceiv'd, he may be ſure of enjoying Felicity Eternal, and Infinite Happineſs. There is then great Gain attends him, if he be not deluded; but there is nothing to loſe in caſe he be, by the Confeſſion of the ungodly themſelves. On the other ſide, a Man who believes not a laſt Judgment, and who lives in the unbelief of it, has nothing to hope for, if he be not deceived, becauſe his greateſt Felicity is to be annihilated; but every thing to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of, if he be under a miſtake. For if at his departure our of the World, he finds there is a God, that there is a Judgment, or a Hell, there cannot be imagin'd a Creature more miſerable.</p>
               <p>Now let any Man judge, whether it be not the Accompliſhment of Extravagance, to make choice of an Opinion, whereby a Man runs the risk of being Eternally Miſerable, and hopes for nothing but Annihilation: And whether, thô there were no certain proofs of a Judgment to come, it were not better for 'em always to demean themſelves, as if they were to be judg'd. I ſay no more; for this is ſufficient to ſhew, that ſince our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> are not aſſur'd that thare is no Judgment, they ought not to build upon this Opinion the <hi>Indifferency</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:179515:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Wherein is examin'd, whether there be any thing True or Falſe, Juſt or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</head>
               <p>AMong thoſe whom I call <hi>Indifferent Men,</hi> there are ſome who believe, that there is nothing True or Falſe, Juſt or Unjuſt, ſo that it is lawful to do whatever a Man plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to embrace that Religion that agrees moſt with their Intereſts. Who could ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that in our Age there ſhould be People that ſhould go about to introduce ſuch Scepticiſm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Religion. There is nothing True, ſay they: Yet at leaſt, according to their Sentiments, it muſt be true, that there is nothing True. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, is it not True, that they who maintain this Argument, have a Being, that they are Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls, and extended Bodies; That it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible a Thing ſhould be, and not be at the ſame time, that Two and Two make Four, and that the Whole is bigger then the Part? Certainly, there is no body ſo extravagant as to deny it. We do not diſpure of this matter, will the <hi>Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Men</hi> ſay; but of things that concern Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, I grant it. 'Tis already very much; that they will confeſs that there is ſomething True; but ſtill it is not true, that there is a God; that this God is moſt Perfect, moſt Juſt, Omnipotent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At leaſt, it is no more True, then to ſay, there is no God, or, that this God is an imperfect Being and Unjuſt.</p>
               <p>I do not believe that theſe Skepticks dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, unleſs they will ſpeak againſt their own
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:179515:35"/>Conſciences. For then there is nothing ſo eaſie as to deny every thing, and to maintain at Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day that the Sun is not riſen, or that a Circle is a Square. I am well aſſur'd, that if our <hi>Pyrrho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> would ſpeak ſincerely, they would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that it is alſo true, that God ought to be ſerv'd, and that, in ſuch a manner as is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his Nature. They are therefore moſt groſly miſtaken, who aſſert, that there is nothing of Truth. In ſhort, every Propoſition ought to be True or Falſe. It is True, when it affirms or denies nothing of a ſubject, but what we ought to affirm or deny. It is Falſe, when it affirms or denies what ought not to be affirm'd or deny'd. But is it not certain, will our Skepticks ſay, that upon every Subject we may find out Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> equally ſtrong and convincing? I grant there are ſeveral Subjects upon which Men may argue variouſly; inſomuch that they ſhall be at a great loſs which ſide to take, before they have carefully weigh'd and conſider'd the Arguments on both ſides. I confeſs alſo, that there are ſome very evident Truths that have been diſputed among Philoſophers; among others, ſome have deny'd Motion. Wit loves to ſport ſometimes, and endeavours to obſcure by So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſms, Things the moſt plain and perſpicuous: but I deny, that what is ſaid on both ſides is equally ſolid, and that it is fit to compare So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſms with good Arguments. There are ſome propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tions to which we cannot refuſe our aſſent; and ſome that we cannot deny without acting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Light of our Underſtanding. There are ſome that are not ſo apparent, and others that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:179515:35"/>oppoſe Reaſon. All that our Skepticks ſay, does but teach us, that we ought to ſtand upon our Guards, and not to haſten our Judgment with too much precepitancy, but to ſuſpend it, till Conviction, and our Underſtanding force us from that Heſitation. So that I extremely approve the Rules ſet down by a Philoſopher of our Age, who would have us, when we propoſe any thing, not only carefully to examin the Thing, and to determin nothing till after we have well thought upon it, but alſo to ſee.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Whether it be not true, that we believe the thing in diſpute for no other Reaſon, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Maſters have ſo taught us.</item>
                  <item>2. Whether it be not True, that we believe the thing upon no other account, but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was approved by a great number of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have gain'd a Repute in the World.</item>
                  <item>3. Whether it be not True, that we believe the thing, by reaſon of long Uſe and Cuſtom; that is to ſay, Becauſe we have ſuch an <hi>Idea</hi> in our heads from our Education and our Infancy, and for that we judge that ſeveral things were True, becauſe they were conformable to that <hi>Idea.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Whether it be not True, that we conclude the Truth in Diſpute, from a ſuppoſed Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſuch a one which we never examin'd.</item>
                  <item>5. Whether it be not True, that we believe the Thing, only becauſe it is a Novelty.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe are the Precautions which we ought to take; but 'tis an extravagancy, to maintain that there is nothing True. We haturally all of us love Truth, and we deſire to find it out. Is it then to be thought that this Deſire ſhould be En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:179515:36"/>in all Men, if there were nothing True or Falſe?</p>
               <p>What I aſſert of Truth, I alſo ſpeak of Juſtice or Injuſtice; that is to ſay, that there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Juſt or Unjuſt, and that there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary diſtinction between Good and Evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that which is Honeſt, and that which is not ſo.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, were there no reaſon for this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it muſt be ſaid, that Paracides and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, to ſpeak Properly, Commit no Crime; that 'tis the ſame thing whether we Hate or Love God; whether we Honour our Parents, or Cut their Throats.</p>
               <p>Now I beſeech ye, Can ſuch Sentiments en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our Thoughts without Horror? They will ſay, perhaps, that this Horror proceeds from the Prejudices of Education. But if it be ſo, How comes it to paſs, that the ſame Horror is Univerſal among all People, thô their Education be very different?</p>
               <p>They will likewiſe object, that Legiſlators, and Governors of States and Kingdoms have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken great Care to infuſe into the People, that there is ſomthing of Juſt and Unjuſt. But is it probable, that thoſe Legiſlators could have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed ſo exactly without conſulting together, to impoſe the ſame things upon ſo many different People? That they were ſo ſufficiently powerful, as to engrave their Precepts in the bottom of the Peoples Hearts; or ſo politick and cunning, as to inſpire into 'em that niceneſs, as to make it a ſcruple of Conſcience to diſobey 'em? Or how is it to be imagin'd, that ſo vaſt a number of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:179515:36"/>People would entertain and uphold Laws that recompence Virtue, and puniſh Vice, but which are otherwiſe ſo very ſevere and irkſom, unleſs there were a Natural Light, which makes all Men agree in the point of their Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Had not Man a Natural Idea, and a Natural Love of Duty, Men might be made believe in that particular, whatever Impoſture pleas'd; and they might be perſuaded, that Ingratitude, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidiouſneſs, and Blaſphemy, are Virtues which ought to be eſteemed; Nevertheleſs, nothing is more Impoſſible.</p>
               <p>It will be ſaid, that ſeveral Nations have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Bad Laws as well as good. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that never any Legiſlators could im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe Laws which were altogether bad. The Lawgivers concern'd, ſtill intermix'd 'em among the good ones, and endeavour to ſupport 'em with good Principles, already in vogue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People: They have alſo made uſe of Force to eſtabliſh or preſerve 'em; ſo that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to unjuſt Conſtitutions is a proof of the Neceſſity of thoſe which are juſt.</p>
               <p>But let us preſs a little cloſer upon our <hi>Pyrrhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> Either they are bound to obey their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or they are not. If they are not oblig'd, their Reaſon ſtands 'em in no ſtead, and it is in Vain that Nature has made 'em Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. If they are bound, they do ill when they withdraw their Obedience from it. Therefore there is a difference between Good and Evil. It will be objected, no doubt, that Reaſon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates to one Man that the Thing is Good, to another, that it is Bad, ſo that it depends purely
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179515:37"/>upon humour. But certain it is, that there are ſome things good, and others bad, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Mankind. So that in that reſpect, our Reaſon is beyond all Controul. Moreover, the Force of that Objection reaches no farther then to prove, that all Men have not the ſame parts; and that they do not all diſtinguiſh Good and Evil as they ought to do. But they are not able to prove from thence that there is nothing Juſt or Unjuſt: On the other ſide, 'tis a certain proof, that Men have naturally an Idea, that there is ſome thing Juſt, and ſome thing which is not ſo.</p>
               <p>Let us then put this Queſtion to our Skeptics, whether the Creature owes Nothing or Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to his Creator? No Man durſt hitherto maintain, that the Creature owes him. Nothing. If any thing, he is oblig'd to performances, and if he do not pay what he owes, he does ill. There are ſome things, which are good in themſelves, and others which are not ſo; and therefore 'tis to build a Sandy Foundation, to pretend to prove that Religions are Indifferent, becauſe there is nothing by Nature Good or Evil.</p>
               <p>I ſhall add but one word more in Oppoſition to thoſe who aſſert, that to ſpeak properly, there is nothing Juſt but what agrees with our Intereſt, or with the Public Benefit. This Opinion is very abſurd, 1. Becauſe, that Right Reaſon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us frequently to act againſt our own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, and Commands us to do thoſe things that prove miſchievous and hurtful to us, as it prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits us from other things that might redound to our Benefit, yet after we have followed the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179515:37"/>of Right Reaſon, receive a great deal of Comfort and Satisfaction for ſo doing. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, that if Profit and Advantage were to be the Chief Rule of our Actions, our firſt Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and laſt End, there would be no Truth nor Sincerity between Man and Man, it would be in vain that Nature has made us Sociable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and it would behove us rather to ſay, that Men were Created to be Robbers and Poiſoners, when their Intereſt requir'd it; which is the moſt Horrid thing in the World. 3. Becauſe, that if Profit were to be the Rule of all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and if the Idea of Honeſty were a meer Illuſion, all Men in the World would never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh as they do between Profitable and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; and Men the moſt Corrupt would never be ſenſible from time to time, of the Force of that Idea. For this is a convincing Proof, that this Idea is one of the Firſt Eſtabliſhments of Nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Againſt thoſe who believe, that the Truth is Conceal'd.</head>
               <p>IN the Croud of our <hi>Indifferent-Men,</hi> there are ſome who dare not poſitively maintain, that there is nothing true; but they believe that Truth is plung'd in <hi>Democritus</hi>'s Well, and that it is entirely Conceal'd from Men; and that therefore, 'tis no great matter what Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we Embrace, becauſe we know not where Truth reſides.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:179515:38"/>
               <p>But what we have already ſaid in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter, ſhews the Abſurdity of this Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For we have ſufficiently prov'd, that all theſe Truths are not conceal'd from Men, but that there are a great Number, who are clearly Convinc'd, that there is a God, that he is moſt Wiſe, Almighty, moſt Perfect, that we ought to ſerve him, and that we ought to do as we would be done by.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, it would be a ſtrange thing if there were no Truths; that God had given us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding capable to reach and apprehend 'em, and yet that he ſhould not have reveal'd 'em to us, or that he ſhould not have fix'd a kind of Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between thoſe Truths and our Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, to know when they meet, and when they do not meet, together. In like manner, it would be a ſurprizing thing, that God ſhould have Created Light, and given Men Eyes to ſee it, yet never produce it into the World. The Idea which we have of God, is, that he is a Being both good and gracious by doing good. Now what Idea can we have of a God that has made Creatures, and yet would conceal himſelf from 'em; who has endu'd 'em with Reaſon to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Truth, yet had not reveal'd to 'em thoſe Truths which it moſt concern'd 'em to know?</p>
               <p>If it be objected, that there are an infinite number of Truths which Man can never dive into by the Light of Nature, we muſt be forc'd to grant it, becauſe we cannot deny it. 'Tis not to ſpeak of the Myſteries of the Trinity and Incarnation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which the Chriſtian Religion has taught us, and into which the wit of Man can
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179515:38"/>never penetrate; there are ſeveral other Truths leſs difficult to apprehend; which Men however had been altogether ignorant of, had it not been for Revelation. For Example, Men might naturally know, by the Light of Reaſon only, that there is a God, and that this God ought to be ador'd, but he knows not after what manner this Sovereign Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will be ador'd. He knows that he is a Sinner, but he knows not by the Light of Nature, which way to make his Peace with God. He may know that his Soul is Immortal; but he knows not what will become of his Soul: nor had the Pagans in this Particular any other then confus'd Idea, which may be well judg'd by what the Emperor <hi>Adrian</hi> ſaid. And it appears by the Diſcourſes of <hi>Socrates,</hi> that Wiſe Philoſopher, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death, that he was no better inform'd upon this Subject then the Emperor.</p>
               <p>It is certain then, that Revelation is neceſſary; but we aſſert alſo, that this Revelation has been made; and that God has manifeſted to Men whatever is requiſite for 'em to know, to the end they may be happy; and this is that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which we meet with in the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:179515:39"/>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Divinity of the Scripture.</head>
               <p>IN regard there are ſeveral Perſons that will not acknowledge the Books of the Old and New Teſtament to be Divinely inſpir'd, 'tis neceſſary to ſettle the Confirmation of this Truth before we go any farther; and this is that which we ſhall ſuccinctly undertake in this Chapter, until we ſhall have accompliſh'd it more at large, with God's permiſſion, in another Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>Nor do I believe it to be a thing ſo difficult to demonſtrate the Divinity of the Scriptures, as at firſt it ſeems to be. For either they muſt ſay, that God has not made himſelf known, or that he has reveal'd himſelf, but that we know not where this Revelation is: or elſe they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that it is to be found in the Scriptures. They cannot ſay, that God has not made himſelf known, for we have prov'd in the foregoing Chapter, that they cannot maintain it, without having a very unworthy Idea of God. They cannot ſay, that God has reveal'd himſelf, but that they know not where this Revelation is. For wherefore ſhould God have reveal'd himſelf, if the Book be not known wherein he has declar'd his Will to Men? Therefore they muſt confeſs, that God has made himſelf known in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament. For they cannot tell us of any other; becauſe there is no other which has more the Characters of Divinity; and thoſe Characters
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179515:39"/>are ſo viſible, that he muſt willingly hoodwink his own Eyes that cannot ſee 'em.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, what could be deſir'd in a Book of which God was the Author, then what is found in the Sacred Writings? Who is there that would not look upon it as a Divine Work? <hi>A Book</hi> that teaches us Truths ſo Extraordinary, ſo Sublime, that Men could never otherwiſe have been able to have invented; Yet ſuch as have a ſtrict Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence and Tye however with the Common Notions, which Nature, or rather the God of Nature has imprinted in our Minds; and which teaches 'em in a manner ſo lofty and ſo plain at the ſame time, that tho' there ſeem not to appear in it any Ornaments of Vulgar Eloquence, yet there is all that human Art can afford Us; a Sovereign Authority which Imprints reſpect in the Soul of him that reads it, and a winning Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility, which attracts and captivates their Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that gives us a greater Idea of God, then can be conceiv'd; that deſcribes him to us as a Spirit, that has no Communication with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, an Infinite Spirit that is every where, an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Being, that does all things; that Created the World, and ſuſtains it by his Providence; who is the Ruler of all Events, the abſolute Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all things, the Judge of Men and Angels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> which clearly Unfolds to us, what Human Reaſon would never have diſcover'd but very imperfectly, which never pronounces any Cenſures, nor gives any Cenſures, but what the Conſcience finds to be moſt juſt; that promiſes nothing but what the Conſcience deſires; that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:179515:40"/>threatens nothing but what the Conſcience dreads: and does it not thence appear, that the Author of the Conſcience is the Author of this Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that Humbles Man before God, by giving him to underſtand his emptineſs, his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found wretchedneſs, his natural Corruption and Sin: that romages the very Secrets and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments of our Souls, to ſhew us our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd Vices, our Vanity, our Pride, our Self-Love, our Love of the World, our Love of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, the Seeds of Incredulity and Prophaneneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that combats all ſorts of Sins, not one excepted, not ſo much as the ſlighteſt; and ſeveral that were unknown to the moſt auſtere Sects of Philoſophers; not ſo much as a Glance or a Thought eſcapes it; it aſſails all the Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Concupiſcence, and all Appearances of Evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that is not contented to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſcribe us an exterior Holineſs, but which reqûires that our Souls ſhould be as pure as our Bodies, and that we ſhould exalt our Virtue to an Heroick Degree, and be like God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that requires that we ſhould have no other Rule but the Law and Will of God, and no other end but his Glory, and which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts from us, that we ſhould principally, and above all things in the World, love the Author of our Being, and that we ſhould love our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor as our Selves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that has nothing of Contradiction in all the Parts of it; and which preſents to our Eyes the <hi>Idea</hi> of a Wiſdom, like to that which is obſerv'd in this vaſt Univerſe; thô they who
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:179515:40"/>wrote it, never had any commun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ication one with another, but were ſeparated by long Intervals of Ages, which ſhews that they were all inſpir'd with the ſame Spirit, and that they had a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Maſter over 'em, who precided over the whole work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> which has foretold extraordinary Events before they happen'd; and with ſo much certainty, that you would rather take it to be a recital of things paſt, then a prediction of things to come: which ſhews us, that it ſprings from a Spirit, before which all things are preſent, which ſees all things, and which clearly ſhines in the darkneſs of Futurity, in regard that nothing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens which it has not ordain'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> which having diſcover'd to Man, that he is Criminal, and Guilty before an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Majeſty, which muſt be atton'd, teaches him afterwards the true means by which he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to his Judge, and ſhews him a Divine Perſon, that deſcends from Heaven to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him Human Nature like his own, who under that Nature ſuffers a cruel Death; who by that Death ſatisfies the Juſtice of God, extinguiſhes the Heat of his Wrath, and makes an Attonement for our ſins, which the Blood of Bulls and Goats, nor all the Purifications of the Law were never able to expiate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that appeaſes all the troubles of the Soul, which all the Books in the World were never able to do; which ſecures us againſt all our Terrors, cauſed by the Confideration of our Sins, the thoughts of Death, and of a Judgment to come, and fills us with that Peace and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:179515:41"/>which neither can be expreſs'd nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> wherein the Doctrine contain'd ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies all the neceſſities of the Soul, and ſatisfies all her deſires; for there is no queſtion to be made, but that a Book, where our Soul, whoſe Deſires are Infinite, finds plenary ſatisfaction, muſt be the Production of a Deity, who being only able to know what we would deſire, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able himſelf alone to content us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> the Doctrine of which produces ſuch extraordinary Effects, that when it is once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into our Hearts, there is nothing able to ſhake our Conſtancy and our Faith; no, not the moſt cruel of Torments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> whoſe Doctrine has been receiv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, maugre all the Efforts of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, thoô it were only divulg'd by Fiſhermen and Toll-gatherers, and for Enemies met with the moſt Eloquent Orators, the moſt refin'd Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, moſt potent Kings and Emperors, who perſecuted, and put to the moſt cruel of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thoſe that preach'd it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Book,</hi> that has been confirm'd by an Infinite-number of Miracles, and by the Blood of a vaſt number of Martyrs, of all Orders, of both Sexes, of all Conditions, of all Ages.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>A Book,</hi> that to this very day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it's priſtin Veneration, thô no endeavours have been omitted to obliterate it, while ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Works have periſh'd, which one would have thought would have endur'd as long as the Sun.</p>
               <p>If this be not the work of God, let 'em tell us, what is a Divine Book, or let 'em ſhew us
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179515:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>any others, wherein all theſe Characters meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But that's more then ever they will be able to do.</p>
               <p>'Tis certain then, that God is reveal'd to Men and that this Revelation is found in the Books of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Clearneſs of the Holy Scripture.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome Men, who acknowledge the Divinity of the Scripture, but they ſay, 'tis ſo obſcure, that no Body can diſcover by it, which is the true Religion; that there never was any Heretick but vaunted of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earing his Paradoxes, upon the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles. So that no Man can be confident from thence, what Religion to fix up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on becauſe all the Religions in the World are not equally to be prov'd by the Holy Scripture. According to which Opinion we may as well ſay, that the Oracles of God are like thoſe of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bills, and that it fares with the Holy Ghoſt as with the <hi>Apollo</hi> of the Pagans, whoſe Anſwers were ſo obſcure, that they might well be taken in two oppoſite Senſes.</p>
               <p>I do not, however, believe that they who are of this Opinion, will preſume to maintain, that Paganiſm and Mahometiſm can be prov'd by Script<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, or that Judaiſm is to be found in the Books of the New Teſtamon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And therefore they muſt acknowledg, that it ought not to be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179515:42"/>an indifferent Thing to 'em, whither they be Turks, Pagans or Jews, but that they ought to embrace the Chriſtian Religion. 'Tis one point gain'd then, that we have brought 'em to be Chriſtians, but we muſt not ſtop there. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they who aſſert the Scripture to be ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, that they cannot thereby apprehend which is the true Religion, have a ſtrange <hi>Idea</hi> of God. For God has given us the Scriptures to ſome end: this they cannot deny, unleſs they will doubt of the Wiſdom of the moſt perfect Being. This <hi>End</hi> he teaches us himſelf by his Servants. <hi>All things,</hi> ſays <hi>St. Paul,</hi> Rom. 15.4. <hi>were written for our Inſtruction, to the end, that through Patience and Conſolation in the Holy Scriptures, we might have hope.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle declares, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>That the whole Scripture is Divinely inſpir'd, and properly for Teaching, Convincing, Correcting and Inſtructing according to Juſtice, to the end the Man of God may be accompliſh'd, and perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in every good work.</hi> But I beſeech ye, what Inſtruction, what Conſolation can a Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from a Book ſo obſcure as the Scripture, if what our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> aſſert, be true? Or can a work of that nature accompliſh a Man of God? 'Tis the Pleaſure of God that we ſhould have recourſe to his Word, as to the Rule of our Faith and our Manners; the Apoſtles Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thoſe that teach any other Doctrine, and command the Faithful not to hold communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſuch ſort of People, and pronounce the Peace of God upon all thoſe that walk according to that Rule. But how is it poſſible that this Book can ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rve for a Rule, if it be ſo extreamly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:179515:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>obſcure? and why ſhould Anathema's be thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd out againſt all thoſe that teach any of her Doctrine then what is contain'd therein, if we cannot preciſely know what it is that it teaches?</p>
               <p>Either God could not clearly reveal himſelf to Men, or elſe it was not his Pleaſure ſo to do. Can it be faid, that he could not? What is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to the Father and Author of Light? who himſelf has placed the Sun and the Stars in the Firmament, to enlighten the whole World? Can it be ſaid, that it was not his Pleaſure? How! Would not the Father of Mercy, whoſe Goodneſs is Infinite, vouchſafe to make his Will clearly known to Men, to the end they may pay him faithful Obedience? If ſo, wherefore does he threaten pains Eternal to thoſe that diſobey him, and believe not in his Word?</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs, there are many things obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliver'd in Holy Scripture. It contains pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Depths and Myſteries. And it was the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God it ſhould be ſo, to humble our Lofty Reaſon pufft up with Knowledge; to waken our Minds, that fall aſleep when we meet with no difficulty; to oblige us to Pray, Meditate, and Labour; make us the more earneſtly wiſh for that day when we ſhall be fill'd with the knowledge of all things the moſt obſcure. But if there be things obſcure and difficult in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there are others that are moſt clear and eaſie. It proportions it ſelf to all, and offers it ſelf to all. There is in it a Simplicity that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſes it ſelf to the moſt Simple, and a Loftineſs that exerciſes the moſt Learned. All indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently drain from it; but far from being able to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:179515:43"/>empty it by filling our ſelves, we always leave behind Abyſſes of Knowledge and Wiſdom, which we adore, without being able to comprehend 'em. <hi>Thus the Loftineſs of it aſtoniſhes the Haughty; it awakes the Sloathful by the Importance of the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concerning which it treats; The Difficulties contain'd in it exerciſe the Induſtry, and it nouriſhes the Wiſe with its Illuminations,</hi> according to the ſaying of St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> which is that which Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> very well explains in his Letter to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Seville,</hi> when he ſent him his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals upon <hi>Job. As the word of God,</hi> ſays he, <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſes Myſteries able to exerciſe the Wits of the moſt clear-ſighted, ſo it alſo contains clear and evident Truths, proper to feed the ſimple and leſs Learned. Outwardly it has wherewithal to give Milk to Babes, and within her Secret Folds and Concealments ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to raviſh with admiration the ſublimeſt of Human Wits; like a River ſo ſhallow in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that a Lamb may wade over, and in others deep enough for an Elephant to Swim.</hi> And in the Preface to the 20th Book of his Morals, he thus expreſſes himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Scripture is incomparably ſuperior to all other Doctrine; not only for that it brings us Tidings of nothing but certain Truths; not only becauſe it calls us to a Heavenly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, becauſe it changes the Hearts of thoſe that read it, by withdrawing 'em from Terreſtrial Deſires, and inflaming 'em with a Deſire of Heaven; but alſo for that at the ſame time that it exerciſes the more Intelligent and perfect with Obſcure Texts, it Careſſes and Comforts the more imperfect and feeble Underſtandings
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:179515:43"/>with the ſweetneſs and eaſineſs of its precepts. It is neither ſo obſcure as to ſcare Men from reading it, nor ſo eaſie to be underſtood, as to incur Contempt. The more Familiar it is, the leſs it diſreliſhes: the more Men Meditate upon it, the Higher Value they put upon it. It aſſiſts our Souls by the Simplicity of Words, and the Sublimity of the Sence which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contain'd; and ſeems to grow and exalt it ſelf by degrees, as they that read it raiſe themſelves and grow in Underſtanding. So that the moſt Ignorant, and they that have the meaneſt parts underſtand ſomething in it, and the Learned always meet with Novelty.</q> To which we may add what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, That it propoſes to us whatever is moſt neceſſary for the Conduct of our Lives; that it explains and illuſtrates it ſelf, by expounding clearly to us in ſome parts, what it delivers but obſcurely in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. This pious Biſhop every where inſinuates, that the Scriptures manner of teaching is propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to all ſorts of Conditions, and to the Underſtanding of Readers the moſt ſimple, and of meaneſt Capacities; that it invites all Men by a plain and ſimple Diſcourſe to ſeek therein, wherewith to nouriſh themſelves with apparent Truths, and wherewith to exerciſe themſelves in the diſcovery of thoſe that are conceal'd; that if it puts to ſhame the Vanity of the Haughty, by reaſon of the ſublimity of it, to which they cannot reach; if the Depth of it affrights and terrifies thoſe that ſtrive to penetrate into it; it nouriſhes by Vertue of thoſe Truths wherewith it is repleniſh'd, the moſt exalted Souls, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:179515:44"/>Children that Food which is proper for 'em, through the Familiarity wherewith it ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>To be convinc'd of the Clearneſs of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, there needs no more then to reflect upon what is taught us therein. Does it not clearly teach us to know an Eternal God, ſovereignly Good, moſt Wiſe, moſt Potent, and moſt Juſt, who has expanded the Heavens, and laid the Foundations of the Earth by his Almighty Power; who ſuſtains all things by his Word, who has created Men and Angels, who preſerves 'em, and and is to judge 'em? Does it not clearly ſhew us the profound Miſery of Man, his Corruption, his Sin, his inability to free himſelf from the ſad Condition he is in? Does it not clearly ſhew us what Chriſt has done for us, to deliver us out of this Inconvenience; how he came into the World to put on our Nature; how he dy'd for our Sins; how he roſe for our Juſtification; how he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Gloriouſly into Heaven, to prepare a Place for us; and how he is to return to open our Tombs, and to raiſe us to his Eternal Sanctuary? Does it not clearly tell us what Bleſſings this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Saviour has merited for us, Pardon for our Sins, our Peace with God, the Gift of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Salvation, Eternal Redemption, and Infinite Glory? Laſtly, Does it not clearly ſhew us, what God requires from us, Faith, Repentance, Hope, Charity, Patience, and all thoſe Virtues which we ought to put in Practice, and all thoſe Vices from which we ought to abſtain.</p>
               <p>Lot Men judge after all this, whether they have any reaſon to accuſe the Holy Scriptures of Obſcurity. Certainly, if there be any obſcure
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179515:44"/>Places, it ought to be acknowledg'd, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is neceſſary for our Knowledge is clearly explain'd. So that 'tis the ſame thing with the Holy Scripture as with the Book of Nature; both contain things which all the World may know; others require Application and Study; others cannot be comprehended.</p>
               <p>But is it not true, ſay our <hi>Indifferent Men,</hi> that all Hereſies may be prov'd by Scripture? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the Hereticks boaſt their drawing their Opinions from Divine Sources; the more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly to deceive thoſe that they have a mind to ſeduce. Such were <hi>Arrius, Neſtorius, Eutyches, Macedonius, Socinus,</hi> and an Infinite Number of others. But tho' theſe Hereticks vaunted their having aſſerted nothing but what they extracted from Divine Writings; 'tis falſe that their Proofs are ſolid; and that they have any reaſon to infer from thence that the Scripture is ſo obſcure, that all ſorts of Opinions may be drawn from thence. This only ought to engage us to take all the Care imaginable to underſtand it aright; not to purſue our own Prejudices; not to expound the Scripture according to our own Paſſions. Not to read it, on purpoſe to pick out Opinions which we have already invented; but ſuch as we ought to have; to examine well the Meaning of the Holy Spirit, and the end which he propoſes to himſelf; to compare Scripture with Scripture; and not to ſtudy it with a deſign to ſet up new Opinions to ſignalize our ſelves in the World, and gain Diſciples; but only with a proſpect of advancing in the Knowledge of the Myſteries of our Salvation, and in the Study of Piety.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:179515:45"/>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Againſt thoſe who believe, that although the Truth be clearly explain'd in Scripture, yet that it ought to be indifferent to us what Religion we embrace.</head>
               <p>WE have hitherto diſputed againſt thoſe that will not acknowledge the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Scripture, or who would make it uſeleſs to us. Now our main Buſineſs is, to contend with Thoſe who agree, that the Truth is ſufficiently explain'd in Scripture; but ſtill they believe that we have no occaſion to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our ſelves about the Choice of a Religion; or at leaſt, they live as if they believ'd ſo. This ſort of <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> is very numerous; ſo that 'tis but juſt, that we ſhould apply our ſelves a little to refute 'em.</p>
               <p>I draw my firſt Argument againſt 'em from hence, that we ought always to prefer Truth before a Lye; and that we ought always to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that Truth, when we have once attain'd to the Knowledge of it. For if it be ſo, then it follows of neceſſity, that all Religions ought not to be Indifferent.</p>
               <p>It will be no difficult Thing to apprehend the Force of this Inference, if it be but conſider'd, that all Religions, being contrary the one to the other, and ſtill accuſing each other of Falſhood, it muſt be neceſſarily concluded, that Truth is one of theſe Religions, and Falſhood in the Reſt. If then we ought to prefer Truth before Falſhood, we ought to abide in that Religion where Truth
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179515:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall be found, and avoid all the reſt as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sects.</p>
               <p>This Propoſition, that Truth is always to be preferr'd before Falſhood, and that we ought to embrace the Truth when we have once attain'd to the Knowledge of it, ſeems to have no need of Proofs. For where is that Man who will preſume to aver that Truth is to be preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Falſhood? Had God reveal'd to us which Sect of Philoſophers is the True one, there is no Perſon but would willingly ſubmit. 'Tis for the finding out theſe Philoſophical Truths, that the Learned read with ſo much Application what the Ancient Philoſophers have written, and what the Moderns have diſcovered, and 'tis with that deſign that they make ſo many Experiments at this Day. Now then, if it be true in things that concern Philoſophy, and which are of no uſe in Reference to Salvation; How much more ought we to lave Truth in matters of Religion, where our Sovereign Good lies at Stake. More eſpecially, ſince God has taught us what is true, what is falſe, what pleaſes, and what offends him. The Love of Truth ſeems to be born with us, ſo that even Children love it. 'Twas ſo highly eſteemed among the Pagans, that their Authors make no Scruple to aſſert, that 'tis the Richeſt Preſent that God ever made Mankind; that it renders Mortals equal to God; and that if a Soul and Body were to be attributed to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity, Truth muſt be allowed him for the Soul, and Light for the Body. They alſo deemed themſelves ſo Happy, when they found it out, that they offer'd Hecatombs to their Gods, to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:179515:46"/>return 'em Thanks for the Diſcovery of ſo preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Treaſure. Who would not be aſtoniſhed then, that in the Chriſtian World, there ſhould be perſons ſo daring as to maintain, that in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Falſhood might be ſometimes preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Truth, though upon all other occaſions of Life they prefer Truth before Falſhood, and take no delight in being deceiv'd. Their Crime is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſo much the Greater, for that God is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Truth, and the Devil the Father of Lyes: ſo that no Man can prefer Falſhood before Truth, but he muſt prefer the Devil before God; which is not a thing to be thought of without Horror.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Indifferent Men,</hi> that very well perceive the force of this Argument, make uſe of all their Wit to anſwer it.</p>
               <p n="1">I. They ſay in the Firſt place, that there is no Religion, which has not ſome Truths; and therefore They, who upon ſome occaſions, and as their Intereſts require, embrace new Religions, cannot be ſaid to embrace Falſhood before Truth, becauſe they always meet with the Choiceſt and moſt Eſſential Truths in all ſorts of Religious Societies.</p>
               <p>This firſt Anſwer, or rather Evaſion, is very abſurd; for the preferring Religions where there are ſome Truths, but withal very great and groſs Errors, before a Religion which is pure, and which teaches us all the moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Truths, is a manifeſt preferring of a Lye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Truth; and this is that which our <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Men</hi> do.</p>
               <p>Now that they may ſee how much they are deceiv'd, I beſeech 'em to conſider,</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:179515:46"/>
               <p n="1">1. That thoſe Truths which are obſerv'd in all Religions, are ſtifl'd in certain Sects, with an innumerable company of Errors, which are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be diſcover'd.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That thoſe General Truths, to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, conſtitute no particular Religion.</p>
               <p>Every Religion, if I may be permitted to ſay ſo, has a <hi>Genus,</hi> and a <hi>Difference.</hi> The <hi>Genus</hi> of all Religions are thoſe principal Truths which are known to all Men, but that which makes the diſtinction, is either the Teaching of other Truths or Errors. So that the Principal Truths are not the Reaſon that a Religion is ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; but either Errors, and then the Religion is falſe; or other Truths, which are not joyn'd to the former, and then the Religion is True. As that which makes a Man to be a Man, is not his <hi>Animoſity,</hi> or his being a Creature; that's his <hi>Genus:</hi> but it is his Reaſon which makes him a Rational Creature. So they who prefer a falſe Religion before a True one, cannot excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſaying, That that ſame very Religion has ſome Truths; becauſe thoſe Truths, as I have ſaid already, to ſpeak properly, conſtitute no Religion.</p>
               <p>But our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> will ſay, that if we ought always to prefer Truth before a Lye, we ought then to quit a Religion wherein we find ſome Errors.</p>
               <p>I anſwer Firſt, That if there be any Religion purer then that which we profeſs, we ought not to be aſham'd of quitting our Religion, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace another. But in the ſecond place, I ſay, we ought to diſtinguiſh between the Errors. There are ſome which are Capital and Mortal,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:179515:47"/>which creep into our Worſhip and our Manners; which diſcompoſe and overturn the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſtianity; but there are others which are not altogether incompatible with Piety; as there are likewiſe two ſorts of Truths; the one which are of higheſt importance, of which we cannot be ignorant and yet be Sav'd; others which are not ſo neceſſary; ſo that without the knowledge thereof, we may one day obtain Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Tis certain, that we ought to abandon a Communion, which deſtroys Eſſentially the Service of God, and which continues obſtinare in Errors, directly oppoſite to the Salvation of Mankind. But we may be ſtedfaſt to a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein are only ſome ſcatter'd Errors of ſmall Importance, contenting our ſelves with not approving thoſe Errors; as in civil Society we refrain from Familiarity with thoſe perſons whom we find to be notoriouſly vicious, becauſe that a Correſpondency with ſuch perſons would be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain to thoſe that make Profeſſion of Honour and Virtue. But with all mildneſs we bear with the defects of thoſe perſons, who not being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly wicked, retain the Tinctures only of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man frailty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place they ſay, that we ought to prefer Truth before a Lye, but that we ought to perfer Peace before Truth. This is an Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that meets with no better luck then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer? 'Tis true that God loves Peace, but ſuch a Peace as is conjoyn'd with Truth, becauſe he is no leſs the God of Truth, then the God of Peace, and for that Peace without Truth is a conſpiracy againſt God; ſo that War is to be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179515:47"/>preferr'd before a Peace that ſeparates us from God. This is no more then what the Pagans themſelves acknowledg'd; and if they have ſaid that Peace is the moſt excellent. Thing in the World; they have likewiſe aſſerted, that we ought never to commit an unjuſt or baſe Act for the enjoyment of it. The love of Peace ought only to encline us to tolerate thoſe Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences that are not guilty of Capital Errors, and ſuch as are incompatible with our Salvation. And therefore we cannot conſent with thoſe ancient Authors, who made ſuch a noiſe about Innocent Opinions, as if they had overturn'd all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. As <hi>Philaſtius,</hi> who lookt upon thoſe as very great Hereticks, who attributed the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to <hi>St. Clement</hi> and <hi>St. Barnahas,</hi> and not to <hi>St. Paul;</hi> and thoſe who did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>David</hi> compos'd the 150 <hi>Pſalms.</hi> We cannot approve Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> who for a Petty Queſtion excommunicated the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> by that means diſmembring the Great and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body of Jeſus Chriſt; which was very well repreſented to him by <hi>Ireneus;</hi> and we believe, as that Biſhop did, that for the ſake of Peace it is much better to bear with the petty defects of the Church, then to violate the Peace of it by correcting the Church; in regard the Miſchief of the Rupture is incomparably much greator then the Fruit which is to be reap'd from the Cenſure of ſuch an Error. But the love of Peace ought never to oblige us to prefer Communions, full of Errors, before another which is much more pure; becauſe nothing ought to be dearer to us then Truth, and for that we ought arwaps
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:179515:48"/>to remember what <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſays, that we never ought to do Evil that Good may come of it. To which we may add, That Truth of it ſelf is not contrary to Peace, and that it is only by Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it is the occaſion of Wars and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions. 'Tis not Truth, but the Corruption of Men, which cauſes War, and is the Fuel of Diſcord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They will ſay in the Third Place, that God always Pardons the Good Intention, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will not deny Salvation to thoſe who prefer Peace before Truth, becauſe they think they pleaſe God in doing ſo. This Third Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is refuted very eaſily by the ſame Scripture, which teaches us, that a Good Intention is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to juſtifie our Actions before God, when we do that which he has forbid us to do. And to be convinc'd of this, there needs no more then to read the Hiſtory of <hi>Saul.</hi> God had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to exterminate the <hi>Amalekites</hi> in ſuch a manner as he enjoyn'd him: Nevertheleſs he ſpar'd the beſt of the Oxen, and the beſt of the Sheep to Sacrifice to the Lord. One would have thought there had been nothing blame-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in this Action. Nevertheleſs, <hi>Samuel</hi> gives him a terrible Reprimand. <hi>Has the Lord,</hi> ſaid He, <hi>as great delight-in Burnt Offerings and Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as in obeying the voice of the Lord? Behold, to obey is better than ſacrifice, and to hearken, then the fat of Rams. For Rebellion is the ſin of witchcraft, and ſtubborneſs is as Iniquity and Idolatry; becauſe thou haſt rejected the word of the Lord, he has alſo rejecte? Thee from being King.</hi> Thus you ſee how his good Intention was rewarded. To this we
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:179515:48"/>may add the Hiſtory recited in the 1ſt of <hi>Kings</hi> chap. 13. A man of God was ſent to <hi>Bethel</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie againſt the Altar of <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> He per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed exactly the Command which had been given him; and becauſe that God had forbid him to eat and drink in that Country, he would not enter into <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Palace. But meeting an old Prophet in his return, who aſſur'd him that an Angel had commanded him from the Eternal, to carry him back to his Houſe, and to give him to eat, the Man of God ſuffered himſelf to be over-rul'd, and went and Din'd with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. He thought that that was no violation of the Firſt Order he had receiv'd, becauſe he made no queſtion of the Truth of what was told him: His Intention was only to obey the Eternal. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, God call'd this Action Rebellion; and at the ſame moment caus'd the Old Prophet, that had brought him back, to pronounce to him the Sentence of his Death, which was afterwards executed by a Lyon. To teach us, not only that there is no Authority which ought to oblige us to violate the Commands of God, but alſo, that our Good Intentions are not ſufficient for our Juſtification. The Hiſtory of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6. confirms the ſame Truth. This Man, ſeeing that the Oxen that drew the Ark, drew it all a one ſide, and fearing that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt Symbol of the Preſence of God ſhould fall, ſtretch'd forth his Hand to hold it. There is no queſtion to be made, but that his Intention was Good. Nevertheleſs God ſmote him, and he dy'd upon the ſpot, becauſe that none but the Prieſts and Levites were to touch the Ark. After
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:179515:49"/>all this, let our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> flatter themſelves with their good Intentions. The Jews believ'd they offer'd a pleaſing ſacrifice to God, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Chriſtians to Death. But can it be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, that their good Intentions were accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God? Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Intention was good when he perſecuted the Church; but was that Intention ſufficient to juſtifie him? He does not think ſo himſelf, ſince he acknowledges his Sin, and Confeſſes that if God had given him Grace, 'twas the moſt Illuſtrious Proof of his Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Three Arguments againſt the Indifferent-Men.</head>
               <p>I Draw a Second Argument againſt theſe who defend Indifferency of Religions from hence, that the Scripture cauſes us to look upon it as a great Crime, for a Man to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don a Truth to the knowledge of which he has once attain'd; and as a Crime that ought to be ſeverely-puniſh'd. For it would never ſpeak in that manner if it were true, that it was lawful to Sacrifice Truth for Peace. There needs no more then to read the Author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Chap. 6. v. 4, 5.6. <hi>For is it poſſible for thoſe who were once enlighten'd and have taſted of the Heavenly Gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted the Good Word of God, and the Powers of the World to come; If they ſhall fall away, to renew them again vnto Repentance:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:179515:49"/>Seeing they Cruoifie to themſelves the Son of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, and put him to open ſhame.</hi> Can People be painted out in blacker Colours then to compane 'em with thoſe that Crucify the Son of God? They are alſo much more to be blam'd; for they who Nail'd to the Croſs the Saviour of the World, had no knowledge of him; but theſe Men Crucifie him, well knowing who he is. The firſt put him to Death in Mortal Fleſh, but the Second Crucifie him in Glory and Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. The Apoſtle ſhews us yet more clearly the Enormity of their Sin, and the puniſhment which they deſerve in the Tenth Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle. <hi>For if we Sin,</hi> ſays he, <hi>wilfully, after we have receiv'd the Knowledge of the Truth, there remains no more ſacrifice for Sins; but a certain fearful looking for Judgment, and fiery Indignation which ſhall devour the Adverſaries. He that deſpis'd Moſes's Law died without Mercy, under two or three Witneſſes. Of how much ſurer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye, ſhall he be thought worthy, who has trodden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot the Son of God, and has counted the Blood of the Covenant wherewith he was ſanctify'd, an unholy Thing, and has done deſpite to the Spirit of Grace? For we know him that has ſaid, Vengeance belongs unto Me, and I will recompence ſaith the Lord.</hi> And again, <hi>The Lord ſhall Judge his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. It is a fearful thing to fall into the Hands of the Living God.</hi> Is it poſſible that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould thus diſcourſe, if there were any Reaſons to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Man to forſake the Truth, without ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and without being afraid of the Judgments of God.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:179515:50"/>
               <p>But becauſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks here of thoſe that quit the Truth voluntarily, and for that perhaps it may be thought, that he diſcourſes not here of thoſe who forſake the Religion which they think moſt pure, to avoid the Miſchiefs they might ſuffer by it, but only of thoſe who quit their Religion without any Neceſſity, there needs no more then to read the following Verſes, where he exhorts the Faithful Hebrews to ſuffer as they had done, rather then renounce the Truth; <hi>But call to remembrance the former days, in which after ye were Illuminated ye endured a great ſight of Afflictions; Partly while ye were made a Gazing-Stock, both by reproaches and Afflictions, and partly while ye became the Companions of them that were ſo us'd. Caſt not away therefore your Confidence, which has great Recompence of reward. For ye have need of Patience,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Which gives me an occaſion to proceed to a Second proof which confirms what we have ſaid, and is taken from the Exhortations of Scripture to die for the Truth. In a word, it would be a great piece of cruelty, to impoſe upon Men a Yoak ſo heavy, without any neceſſity, and to engage 'em to ſuffer all ſorts of Cruelties rather then renounce the Truth, if it might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times abandon'd without a Crime. The Life of Men who are made after the Image of God, and who have been redeem'd by the Blood of his Son, is it ſo meanly to be priz'd, that they ſhould be oblig'd to expoſe it without Compulſive Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? How comes it then to paſs, that Chriſt exhorts us ſo often to carry his Croſs? Whence proceeds it that it is the Firſt Leſſon that he
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:179515:50"/>gives his Diſciples. <hi>If any one will come after me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs and follow me.</hi> Mat. 16.24. <hi>And he that taketh not his Croſs, and follows after me, is not worthy of me. He that finds his Life ſhall loſe it; and he that loſes his Life for my ſake, ſhall find it,</hi> Mat. 10. v. 38, 39. Whence comes it that the Apoſtles ſo often repeat the ſame Exhortation? Wherefore do they command us to bear the Reproach of Chriſt, and to follow the Examples of thoſe that were Ston'd, Saw'd, or ſlain by the Sword, who have wander'd in Deſarts, upon Mountains, and lurk'd in Dens and Caverns of the Earth? Would Wiſe Men, and inſpir'd by God, ſpeak thus, were it an Indifferent Thing what Religion a Man profeſs'd?</p>
               <p>To this Argument I ſhall add another which is taken from a Paſſage in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where that ſame Doctor of the Gentiles pronounces Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's upon all thoſe that ſhould preach any other Goſpel then that which he had preach'd himſelf, though he ſhould be another St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſcended from Heaven, and one of thoſe Bleſſed Spirits that continually behold the Face of God. <hi>But though We, or an Angel from Heaven preach any other Goſpel unto ye, then that ye have received, let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1.8. Certainly, Light is not more oppoſite to Darkneſs, then the words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> are contrary to the Opinions of thoſe againſt whom we diſpute. The Apoſtle anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matizes thoſe thoſe that preach any other Goſpel but that which he has taught. Yet they with whom we diſpute, judge it to be an Indifferent Thing, and of no Importance to embrace a Religion
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:179515:51"/>which teaches another Doctrine, then that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> has taught. This Argument is ſo much the ſtronger, becauſe the Apoſtle thunders out his Curſe againſt people, who only went about to joyn the Religion of Chriſt to that of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Wherein they were far leſs Culpable then our <hi>Indifferent Men,</hi> who would not only joyn <hi>Moſes</hi> with Chriſt, but Jeſus Chriſt with the World; the Religion of Jeſus Chriſt with other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are no more then Human Inventions, and make it their buſineſs to ſerve God and <hi>Mammon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor can I forbear to obſerve in this Place that this Paſſage abſolutely overturns the Opinion of thoſe who imagine, that 'tis enough to believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and to admit of thoſe Truths which are common to all Religions; but that other Things are not of any great Importance; and that there is no neceſſity of diſputing upon that point. For they who are rebuk'd by St. <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledged <hi>Jeſus</hi> for the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> they alſo confeſs'd the moſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Truths of the Goſpel, but he could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade 'em altogether to renounce <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to lay aſide Circumciſion. Nevertheleſs, they are Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Judge then what Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's that Great Apoſtle would now thunder out, were he to deſcend from Heaven. Beſides, that it might be eaſie to prove, that ſhould we grant, what is far from us to do, that it is ſufficient to believe that Chriſt is the Promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> whom the Prophets call the Mighty God, the Father of Eternity, the Eternal of Juſtice, it would follow from thence, that there are Religions which would
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:179515:51"/>be thought to be Chriſtians, which are Falſe Religions, and which we cannot embrace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offending God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Againſt thoſe who believe they make Profeſſion of a Religion, though they believe it to be falſe.</head>
               <p>THE Greateſt part of our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> believe, that without committing any Crime, they may obſerve the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and practiſe the Worſhip of a Falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; that the World may be brought to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with Jeſus Chriſt, and that both the one and the other may be ſerv'd at the ſame Time; like that ſame Emperor who had in his Cloſet the Images of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Abraham, Orpheus,</hi> and <hi>Apollonius:</hi> Or rather like thoſe, (of whom <hi>Adrian</hi> ſpeaks in a Letter to <hi>Servianus,</hi> cited by <hi>Vopiſcus</hi>) who called themſelves Biſhops of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſerved the God <hi>Serapis.</hi> This Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is dangerous, thô eaſie to be refuted, and no leſs eaſie to ſhew that Diffimulation in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion deſerves Rebuke and Cenſure; and that it is Condemned by all the Sacred Writers.</p>
               <p n="1">I. If it were Lawful to diſſemble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal our thoughts concerning Religion, how comes it to paſs, that in the Reign of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel,</hi> God owns none for his Servants, but ſuch as had not bowed their Knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> thô there be no queſtion to be made, but that ſeveral of thoſe who proſtrated themſelves before that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:179515:52"/>Idol, ador'd in their Hearts the True God of <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Wherefore Jeſus Chriſt declares expreſly, that we cannot be of the Number of his Sheep, and follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trangers, <hi>John</hi> 10.4, 5. <hi>And when he putteth forth his own Sheep, he goeth before them, and the Sheep follow him; for they know his Voice; But a Stranger will not follow, but fly from him; for they know not the Voice of Strangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. Whence it comes to paſs, that this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Saviour teaches us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.24. <hi>That we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve two Maſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Wherefore does he expreſly forbid us <hi>to deny him before Men.</hi> Mat. 10.33. Had it not been ſufficient for him to have ſaid, <hi>Who ſhall deny me in his Heart?</hi> Why does he expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo peremptorily, <hi>Whoever ſhall deny me before Men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who ſhall be aſhamed of Me, of him will I be aſhamed.</hi> This is one of thoſe Paſſages that <hi>Avitus</hi> made uſe of againſt <hi>Gandebaud,</hi> who made profeſſion of Arrianiſm, thô he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd Jeſus Chriſt for a God.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Whence comes it to paſs, that Jeſus Chriſt, if we deſire to be his Diſciples, requires of us that we ſhould renounce and forſake our World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Poſſeſſions, and break the ſtricteſt Tyes of Nature that unite us with our Neareſt Relations <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. <hi>If any one comes to me, and hate not his Father and Mother, Wife and Children, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Siſters, yea and his own Life alſo, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be my Diſciple.</hi> And v. 33. <hi>So likewiſe, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be of you, that forſaketh not all he hath, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:179515:52"/>
               <p n="6">VI. Wherefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls thoſe Idolaters who committed any one of thoſe Acts which the Pagans practis'd, 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. If it be ſufficient for a Man to believe in his Heart, without making open Profeſſion of the Truth, how comes it that the ſame Apoſtle Commands us, <hi>to believe in our Hearts, and make Confeſſion with our Mouths unto Salvation,</hi> Rom. 10.9, 10. And that St. <hi>Peter</hi> would have us <hi>Be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy always to give an Anſwer to every Man that asks ye a Reaſon of the Hope that is in you.</hi> 1. Pet. 3.15.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. If it be true that Man may be faithful and practiſe a Falſe worſhip, and obſerve the Ceremonies of a Corrupt Religion, then <hi>might He Drink the Cup of the Lord, and the Cup of Devills,</hi> contrary to the ſaying of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. and have Communion with God, yet walk in Darkneſs, contrary to the Precepts of St. <hi>John</hi> 1 Epiſt. C. 1. v. 6. And a Man may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Good Seed of God into his Heart, and withdraw himſelf in time of Perſecution, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. A Man might be an Idolater and yet be Saved, contrary to what the Apoſtle deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>that Idolaters ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X. He may be regiſter'd in the Book of Life of the Lamb, and adore the Beaſt, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to what is written by St. <hi>John,</hi> Apoc. 13.8. <hi>And all that ſhall Worſhip the Beaſt, whoſe Names are not written in the Book of Life of the Lamb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">XI. If the Opinion of thoſe, againſt whom we Combat, were true, would St. <hi>John</hi> threaten Eternal Torments to the Adorers of the Beaſt?
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:179515:53"/>Apoc. 14. v. 9, 10, 11. <hi>If any Man worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his mark in his Forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink the Wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mixture, into the Cup of his indignation, and be ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimſtone in the Preſence of the Holy Angels, and in the Preſence of the Lamb. And the ſmoke of their torment aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up for ever and ever,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="12">XII. The ſame beloved Diſciple would have placed the <hi>Fearful</hi> at the head of thoſe for whom the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8. Would Jeſus Chriſt threaten to ſpue the Lukewarm out of his Mouth, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.16. For who are the <hi>Fearful</hi> and <hi>Lukewarm,</hi> but they who underſtand the Truth, yet fearing the Hatred and Cruelty of the World, compoſe their outward Behaviour in ſuch a manner, that they make a ſhew of approving a Religion, of which they acknowledge the Falſhood. Such as have an Orthodox Soul, and Lips of Infidels; who will neither be altogether for Jeſus Chriſt, not altogether for the World; who divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves between the One and the Other, and would fain be reconcil'd to Both: In a word, who do that which our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> believe may be done without a Crime.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Whence comes it to paſs, that the Holy Ghoſt condemns thoſe that halt on both ſides, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.21. <hi>Zephan.</hi> 1.5. and thoſe that worſhip and ſwear by the Lord, yet ſwear by <hi>Maloham</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. Wherefore is it, that the Two Apoſtles <hi>St. Paul</hi> and <hi>St. John;</hi> of which the one had
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:179515:53"/>been taken up into Heaven, the Other had ſeen in the Spirit the Heavenly Jeruſalem, Commands us to come out from among the Unfaithful, and from <hi>Babylon,</hi> Apoc. 18.4. <hi>Long out of her my People,</hi> ſays the Lord by <hi>St. John, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that we receive not of her Plagues:</hi> and 2 Cor. 6.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Be ye not unequally yoak'd with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers; for what fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath Righteouſneſs with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs? and what Communion hath Light with Darkneſs? What Concord hath Chriſt with Behal? or what part hath he that believes with an Infidel? What Agreement has the Temple of God with Idols? For ye are the Temple of the Living God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wherefore come out from among 'em, and be ye ſeparate, ſays the Lord, and touch not the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean thing, and I will receive ye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">XV. Laſtly, Wherefore is it, that we are commanded to ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake, and that the Spirit of God makes ſuch large Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to thoſe that ſuffer Perſecution, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>James</hi> 5.10.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
               <p>I add to all theſe Proofs, thoſe Paſſages of Scripture, where the Apoſtles command us to offer to God not only our Souls but our Bodies alſo: and to Glorifie him in our Bodies and our Spirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>I beſeech you therefore, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that ye preſent your Bodies a living ſacrifice holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reaſonable ſervice.</hi> and 1 Cor. 6.20. <hi>For ye are bought with price, therefore Glorifis God in your Body, and in your Spirit, which are Gods.</hi> Is it not a great piece of Sacriledge to refuſe the giving of that to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:179515:54"/>God which belongs to him. He created both our Bodies and Souls, he has redeem'd 'em both, the one in the other; Is it not then juſt, that we ſhould conſecrate both to him? Wherefore ſhould we ſeparate what God has joyn'd, and what he has given us, to the end we ſhould employ it to his Glory? How great a ſin it is, how great a piece of Impiety, to divide our ſelves between God, to whom we owe all things, and the World to which we owe nothing? To deny our Tongues to God, to whom we owe our Lives; and to be aſham'd of calling our ſelves the Servants and Diſciples of Chriſt, who was not aſham'd to call us his Brethren, and who for our ſakes has ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd a moſt cruel and ignominious death.</p>
               <p>To demonſtrate yet more clearly the Falſhood of this Opinion, which I labour to deſtroy, I think it convenient to make theſe few Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is, That it is a ſtrange thing, that there ſhould be ſo many People that make no ſcruple of Lying in Religion, which is a thing of the greateſt Importance, and the moſt Sacred in the World; in regard that Lying is a Vice unworthy a Man of Honour. The greateſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchees become ſenſible of the things of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, if they happen to ſwear a Falſhood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Judge; So true it is, that we have a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Averſion againſt telling a Lye. Who would not wonder then, that Men who are deſirous of Reputation, ſhould not be aſham'd to lye in a thing that is moſt grave and ſerious in the World; the Concern of God himſelf, of Truth and our own Salvation. If a Subject, who gives but the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:179515:54"/>leaſt ſuſpition of an Intention to Revolt from his Prince, and who only lets fall ſome words that will admit of a bad Conſtruction, is handl'd with ſo much ſeverity, in regard that Royal Majeſty is ſo Sacred, that it is not to be injur'd in any manner whatever, without incurring the guilt of a hainous Crime; What greater Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion can a Man commit, then to make a ſhew of being an Enemy to God and his Truth? What Torments ought not they to expect, who are guilty of ſuch Impiety?</p>
               <p>The Second Reflexion is this, That they who diſſemble in Religion, commit a very great crime againſt their Brethren, for they incite 'em by their own example to Apoſtacy, and make 'em believe, that the Religion which they profeſs is the true Religion. So that if they who poiſon the Body, are lookt upon as the wicked'ſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the World; How much more criminal are they who poiſon the Soul; who preſent their Brethren the Mortal Draught, and make a ſhew of Drinking it to the end, that others may not be afraid of ſwallowing it? And what Torments ought not they to fear from Him who threatens to puniſh moſt ſeverely Lyers, and ſuch as give ſcandal to his little Children.</p>
               <p>This Remark is ſo much the more neceſſary becauſe there are ſeveral Perſons who believe, that a Man may abide in a falſe Religion, with a deſign to make known the Truth to thoſe who know it not, wherein they groſly abuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For beſides that, I would willingly ask 'em, whether they can ſpeak it with a ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that they only ſtick to the falſe Religion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:179515:55"/>which they profeſs, on purpoſe to ſhew the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of it, and whether it be not meerly becauſe they find it more advantageous for their Buſineſs, and for the enjoyment of the Conveniencies of Life; I would put this farther queſtion to 'em, were the Firſt of theſe the real Motive that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains 'em, Who is he that has enjoyn'd 'em to extend their Charity ſo far as to expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves willingly to Damnation, out of hopes to convert others? For where is it that God has promis'd to Save thoſe who ſhall turn Idolaters to Save their Brethren? Does not <hi>St. Paul</hi> expreſly ſay, That we ought not to do evil, that good may come of it? But ſo far are they from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting others by adhering to a falſe Religion, that quite the contrary, they confirm 'em in their own Opinion, and corrupt many by their bad Example. They may make good Hypocrites like themſelves, but very rarely good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>The Third Reflexion which I add to the two preceding is this, That if Diſſimulation in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be permitted, and that it be lawful to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that which beſt agrees with our carnal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, we muſt confeſs, that the Martyrs who have laid down their Lives with ſo much Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſuffered ſuch cruel Torments, were all Fools and Madmen, while they rather choſe to loſe their Lives, when there was no neceſſity for it, and periſh in the midſt of conſuming Flames, then to condeſcend to the leaſt comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, thô but in outward ſhew, and buckle to their Perſecutors. But God forbid we ſhould deprive thoſe Chriſtian Hero's of their merited
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:179515:55"/>Honour, and look upon as extravagant, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of all Mortals. Have we not more reaſon to call our <hi>Lukewarm,</hi> and our fearful Chriſtians Fools, who rather chuſe to preſerve their Wealth and Worldly Advantages, then one day to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy thoſe Eternal Felicities which God prepares for thoſe that will be faithful to him; who are more afraid of the preſent then the future; of that which can Kill the Body, then of that which precipitates the Soul into Hell: who are more afraid of Death, then of the cruel Torments of Hell; who prefer the World before God, and Time before Eternity.</p>
               <p>To theſe Three Reflexions I ſhall add a Fourth, which ſeems to me to be of great Importance, that the Inſide can never be good, when the Outſide is evil. And that it is not poſſible for a Man to deny God with his Lips, but he muſt renounce him in his Heart, when he has had time to reflect upon what he has done. I ſay, when he has had time to conſider with himſelf, that I may not oppoſe the Example of <hi>St. Peter,</hi> whoſe Fears ſo far diſturb'd his Mind, that, quite tranſported beyond himſelf, and only ſtudying which way to avoid the danger that threatned him, he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remembred Jeſus Chriſt, nor the Promiſe which he had made him.</p>
               <p>'Twill be no difficult thing to underſtand this 4th Reflexion, if we conſider that 'tis in the Heart that Men take that unhappy and curſed Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to renounce Jeſus Chriſt with their Lips, and that 'tis in their Hearts that they meditate an Accommodation with the preſent Time. 'Tis therefore to no purpoſe for 'em to ſay, that they
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:179515:56"/>reſerve their Hearts for God, and that they ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render 'em entirely to him, thô they forſake his Truth; that they do not renounce him with their Hearts, althô they deny him with their Lips. To talk in this manner is to deceive themſelves; and they who diſcourſe after this manner, are like a Woman, that ſhould ſay, ſhe had bequeath'd her Heart to her Husband, and only made her Body common to her Lovers: Or to a Man that ſhould rend the Reputation of his Neighbor, or Murder him, yet pretend that in his Heart he abhorr'd Murder, Backbiting and Calumny, and that he tenderly lov'd the Perſon whom he had bereft of Life.</p>
               <p>They who diſſemble cannot deny but that the motions of Self-Love prevail over the Impulſes of the Love of God, becauſe they will neither ſacrifice their Wealth, nor their Eaſe to his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. So that if they were always to be judg'd by the Sentiments of their Hearts, they would always deſerve no leſs then Condemnation and Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> An Anſwer to ſome Objections.</head>
               <p>'TIS but reaſonable now to Anſwer ſome Objections which they make us.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is drawn from that which Jeſus Chriſt ſays, <hi>John</hi> 4.24. <hi>God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and Truth.</hi> Therefore, ſay they, God is ſatisfy'd
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:179515:56"/>with the Heart, and with the inſide Worſhip, not requiring exterior Adoration.</p>
               <p>But if this be the Conſequence which is to be drawn from the words of the Saviour of the World, Why does he exhort us to own him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Men, to bear his Croſs, and to ſuffer for him? Certainly, if he required no more then the Heart, wherefore does he exact from us an outward Profeſſion, which expoſes us to a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Diſgraces, and a Thouſand Sufferings? Is our Life of ſo little value, that he would have us to be ſo prodigal of it, when there is no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion? But what Man of Judgement is there, who does not perceive, that his meaning is only to ſhew us, what ſort of Worſhip is moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, and that it his pleaſure, that under the Goſpel we ſhould pay him a Spiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, abſtracted from Matter, and all thoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances which were only proper for the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Church; independant from Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Time, Perſons and Places? Whether it be, that God, filling all the World with the Immenſity of his Being, is no longer to be Ador'd at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> or <hi>Guerezin</hi> only; or whether it be, that, being a Spirit, he is not rightly Honour'd by the Oblations of Bulls and Goats. He neither eats their Fleſh nor drinks their Blood; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be, that which way ſoever you look upon theſe ſorts of Worſhip, they have no Relation or Correſpondence, nor any way ſute with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God; and to ſpeak properly, are no more then ſhadows or Types of the True Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which God requires. This is the Sence of theſe words; and there needs no more to be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:179515:57"/>convinc'd of it then to read what goes before. But we muſt not conclude from thence that God is ſatisfy'd with the Adoration of the Heart, while the Body lies proſtrate at the Feet of a falſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity. This is not a Worſhipping God in Truth, but a Dividing his Adoration, by bequeathing the Inward worſhip to God, and the outward Reverence to ſome other Object. For Truth is no other then the Conformity of Outſide and Inſide. He that has the Outward Formality without the Inward Sincerity is a Hypocrite; and he who ſays he has the Inward without the Exteriour Reality is a Lyer.</p>
               <p>The Second Objection is drawn from what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays in his Epiſtle to the Romans, Chap. 14. v. 22. <hi>Haſt thou Faith, have it to thy ſelf before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there needs no more then to read that Paſſage with attention, and to examine what obliged the Apoſtle to hold that Argument, for any Man to apprehend, that he ſpeaks, there, of the Belief and Faith of a Believer, that Jeſus Chriſt has ſet us at full Liberty; that he has abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd the diſtinction of Days and Meats, that was obſerved under the Old Covenant. St. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore means, that if we find our ſelves in Company with weak People, who would be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized to ſee us take our full Liberty, it would be better to abſtain from the Uſe of thoſe things which God has permitted us, to reſerve our Faith to our ſelves, then to give any Scandal: Becauſe the Diſpute was only concerning Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things; and for that whether we Eat or Eat not, we commit no Sin. But are we thence
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:179515:57"/>to conclude, that the ſame Conduct is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in Things, the uſe of which is ſo far from being Indifferent, that it is abſolutely neceſſary; and ſuch as Jeſus Chriſt recommends to us with ſo much Care; threatening us, withal, with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Puniſhment if we neglect 'em. If that Conſequence were to be drawn from the words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> how comes it to paſs that he exhorts us to make Confeſſion with our Mouths unto Salvation, and to lay down our Lives for the Goſpel? Certainly if it were ſufficient to have faith in the heart, there would be no neceſſity of doing good Works. Contrary to the ſaying of St. <hi>James,</hi> c. 2. v. 14. <hi>What doth it profit, my Brethren, though a Man ſay he hath Faith, and hath not Works? can faith ſave him?</hi> I can hardly think it worth while to refute here the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they draw from another Paſſage of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where he exhorts that Men ſhould make Supplications in all places. For he muſt be blind who underſtands not, that the Aim of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is only to oppoſe thoſe Perſons, who thought the Virtue and Efficacy of Prayers depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Quality of the Place where they were made. It was a general Error of the Pagans, and the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> made a Great Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between Places; in purſuance of what God had ſaid, that he would make choice of one cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain place to fix his Name there. The deſign of St. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore is to reach us, that Jeſus Chriſt had aboliſhed the Moſaic Pedantiſm; that there was no longer any diſtinction to be made of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for Divine Worſhip, in regard there was no Corner of the World that was not fill'd with the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:179515:58"/>Preſence of God, and where he did not favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably hear our Vows. But ſo far was he from pretending that it ſhould be inferr'd from thence, that he forbids all Communion with Idolaters.</p>
               <p>The third Objection is taken from the 6th Chapter of <hi>Baruch,</hi> v.5. and from a Letter which they pretend that <hi>Jeremy</hi> wrote to thoſe that were to be carried away Captive to <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  <q>When you ſhall be enter'd into <hi>Babylon,</hi> you ſhall remain there ſeveral Years, and a long time, even till Seven Generations: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, after that, I will bring ye back in peace. Now you ſhall ſee at <hi>Babylon</hi> Gods of Silver and Wood which ſhall be carried upon Mens Shoulders, and which ſhall terrifie the Nations. Take heed that ye become not in any manner like thoſe Strangers, and that ye be not ſeiz'd with the tear of thoſe Gods, when you ſhall behold the People before and behind, that ſhall adore 'em; but ſay in your hearts, Lord, it is thou alone that art to be ador'd.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In anſwer to this Argument, I will not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether the Book be Canonical or no; thô all Men agree, that the Jews never look'd upon it to be Authentick. That <hi>Meliton, Origen,</hi> Sr. <hi>Hilary, Gregory Nazianzene,</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> make no mention of it, and that St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly rejects it, in his Preface upon <hi>Jeremy.</hi> 'Tis not my buſineſs here to diſcuſs that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, any farther then as it contributes to refute the Miſtake of our Adverſaries. For it ſays ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>Take heed of Conforming in any manner whatever to Strangers.</hi> Would he have trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:179515:58"/>himſelf with any ſuch Exhortation, had it been lawful for the People without offending God, to proſtrate themſelves before the Gods of Gold and Silver, only ſaying in their Hearts, Lord, it is thou alone who art to be ador'd? The enjoyning us to ſay in our Hearts, that God is only to be ador'd, is that a Permiſſion to Worſhip any other but Him? And the Proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves before an Idol, only ſaying what <hi>Jeremy</hi> commands us, is not that a Perfect Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of our ſelves? The Meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of that Holy Prophet is only to inſtruct us, that when we behold Idolaters Worſhipping a Counterfeit Deity, if it be not convenient boldly to Rebuke their Idolatry, for fear of raiſing Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, it behoves us at leaſt to Condemn it in our Hearts, without imitating their Conduct<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or the practiſe or thoſe who behold with delight the Pomp and Magnificence of Idolatrous Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, They make uſe of what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and which we read in the 10th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Acts. Of a Truth, I perceive that God is no reſpecter of Perſons; But in, every Nation he that feareth him and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him.</hi> But that Man muſt very unfortunately deceive himſelf, who ſees not that St. <hi>Peter</hi> means no other Thing, but that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that Salvation was no longer peculiar to the Nation of the Jews; that it was no longer Neceſſary to be of the Poſterity of <hi>Jacob</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh, for a Man to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with God; and that there was no longer
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:179515:59"/>any Diſtinction between the <hi>Jew</hi> and the <hi>Greek,</hi> the <hi>Scythian</hi> and the <hi>Barbarian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ſenſe of thoſe Words. But it is not to be thence inferr'd, that a Man may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with God, let him be of what Religion he pleaſes. Had St. <hi>Peter</hi> had any ſuch thought, would he have taken ſo much pains to Convert People to Chriſtianity? Or have expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ill will of his whole Nation. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> holds the ſame Argument as Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Rom. 10. v. 12, 13. but he had ſaid before, that with the Mouth Confeſſion is made unto Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> An Anſwer to the Examples brought from <hi>Nicodemus, Naaman,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have ſeen the Paſſages of which our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> make uſe; now let us examine the Examples which they bring.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They propoſe to us the Examples of <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Elizabeth, Simeon,</hi> St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> the Bleſſed Virgin, and Chriſt himſelf, who often intermix'd themſelves with the Congregations of the Jews, thô they were very Corrupt, and obſerved the Ceremonies of the Law. But it is apparent that theſe Examples prove nothing of what they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. I confeſs, that <hi>Zachary,</hi> that <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp;c. intermix'd themſelves with the Aſſemblies of the Jews, becauſe it was the will of God that they ſhould pay him their Homage due in his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:179515:59"/>and that there was no command as yet to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the Communion of the Jews. They obſerv'd the Ceremonies of the Law, becauſe thoſe Ceremonies were not then aboliſhed. Jeſus Chriſt was not yet aſcended into Heaven. Then wherefore ſhould they not intermix themſelves in the Aſſemblies of the Jews? The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was there read every Sabbath-Day; they read the Prophets; they offer'd the Sacrifices which God had ordain'd; there was no Idolatry in the Worſhip; they ador'd no other God there but the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Scrib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Phariſees conſtrain'd no Body to believe their Expoſitions of the Law: They could diſtinguiſh the wholſom true Doctrine from the Traditions of Falſe Teachers, and beware of their Leav'n, as Chriſt exhorted his Diſciples. Let 'em now examine what reaſon they have to bring theſe Examples.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They propoſe to us the Example of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who thô he were throughly convinc'd of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Jeſus Chriſt durſt not give him a viſit in Publick, for fear of being expell'd the Synagogue; and the ſame thing is reported of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now upon this Example I obſerve three things. The Firſt is, that thô <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> did not openly take the Part of Jeſus Chriſt, yet they never intermixed in any Society which God had forbid 'em.</p>
               <p>The Second thing is, that <hi>Nicodemus, Joſeph,</hi> and others, who did as they did, are extreamly blam'd in Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 12.42. <hi>Nevertheleſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Chief Rulers alſo many believ'd in him; but becauſe of the Phariſees they did not confeſs him,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:179515:60"/>leſt they ſhould be put out of the Synagogue; for they loved the Praiſe of Men more then the Praiſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Third thing is, that <hi>Nicodemus</hi> oppoſed the Reſolution which the Phariſees took againſt Jeſus Chriſt; that <hi>Joſeph</hi> would never give his conſent; and that both the one and the other, no longer diſſembling their Thoughts, at a Time when the Apoſtles themſelves forſook Chriſt, and that the one deny'd him, the other had betray'd him, openly demanded his Body, and cauſed it to be honourably buried; having the Courage to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs him Dead, whom they durſt not confeſs when he was alive.</p>
               <p>After theſe three Remarks, let us compare our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> with thoſe Illuſtrious Jews. <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> never intermix'd with any forbidden Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. Our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> believe they may do it, and yet commit no Crime. <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> beſtow'd a Publick Funeral upon our Lord Jeſus, and oppoſed the Counſels which the Phariſees took together in Combination againſt him. But our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> are aſham'd to ſpeak for the Truth, or to uphold the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>So that if <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> are blam'd by St. <hi>John,</hi> at a time when they durſt not openly confeſs Jeſus Chriſt, judge how much more Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal our falſe <hi>Nicodemites</hi> are, whoſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is much greater then that of the Jews.</p>
               <p>They Object in the Third Place, the Example of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> who underſtanding the True God, forbore not however from entring into the Temple of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> when his Maſter went thither to pay his Devotions; and they
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:179515:60"/>pretend that <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet gave him leave to comply with the King's Worſhip in Proſtrating himſelf as he did.</p>
               <p>In Anſwer to this Example, I make theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions following,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Naaman</hi> never demanded of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that he might be permitted to diſſemble his Religion before the King of <hi>Syria.</hi> On the other ſide he vow'd, and promiſed that he would Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to no other Deity but the Eternal God, 2. Kings, 5.17. <hi>Shall there not then, I pray thee, be given to thy Servant two Mules Burthen of Earth? For thy Servant will henceforth offer neither burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Offering, nor Sacrifice unto any other Gods, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Second Reflexion is, that <hi>Naaman</hi> made but only one Requeſt; not to enter into the Temple of <hi>Rimmon</hi> when he pleaſed, for that had been a piece of Impiety; but only that it might not be imputed to him for a Crime if he bow'd in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> when his Maſter went to Worſhip there, and lean'd on his hand.</p>
               <p>Theſe two Reflexions already ſhew the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Conduct of our <hi>Indifferent Men,</hi> and that of <hi>Naaman. Naaman</hi> openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that he ſerved the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that he would ſerve none but him. And there is no doubt but that he proteſted the ſame thing to his Maſter, when he related to him the Miracle of his Cure. But our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> believe, that for their better Security, they may profeſs the ſame Religion with Idolaters; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence may have another Object of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip then God, when they are among People who
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:179515:61"/>believe that another ſort of Religions worſhip may be paid to any other Deity. <hi>Naaman</hi> only deſired that he might be permitted to ſerve his Maſter as he was bound in duty to do; but our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> require, that they may be permitted to diſſemble without any other reaſon then for their own Convenience and Profit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naaman</hi> is extreamly troubled in Conſcience about paying this Civil Service to his Maſter, and begs Pardon of God, as being afraid of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting a Sin. His Conſcience had ſuch an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency of Idolatry, that he could not brook any thing which had the leaſt Affinity with it. But our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> make no ſcruple to give themſelves that Liberty which he denied himſelf, and believe they may do that without offending God, which <hi>Naaman</hi> never did; thô <hi>Naaman</hi> was bred up in Idolatry, and had no other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction then what he received from his Cure; whereas our Antagoniſts clearly know the will of God; which will not permit us to doubt, but that <hi>Naaman</hi> will riſe up in Judgment againſt 'em, and that they will undergo ſevere Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>But in regard our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> inſiſt very much upon <hi>Naaman</hi>'s deſiring that God would pardon him, if he proſtrated himſelf in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> when the King his Maſter lean'd upon his Hand, and upon <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s anſwering him, <hi>go in Peace;</hi> as if by thoſe words he gave him leave to do as he deſired, 'tis neceſſary to obſerve in this Place,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Terms in the Original may be underſtood, as if <hi>Naaman,</hi> after he had made a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:179515:61"/>Vow, never from thence forward to Worſhip or ſerve any other then the True God, had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd himſelf in this manner. <hi>I beg of the Lord to pardon this thy Servant, That when my Maſter enter'd into the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon <hi>to proſtrate himſelf there, and that when he lean'd upon my Hand, I alſo proſtrated my ſelf; for that I ſay, let the Lord pardon me.</hi> Reading it in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, there is nothing of Difficulty in the Story; in regard that according to this Verſion, he begs Pardon for what is paſs'd, but not for what is to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>Eliſha</hi> by thoſe Words, <hi>go in Peace,</hi> gave no Permiſſion to <hi>Naaman;</hi> he only diſmiſs'd him with that ſame Complemental Form of Speech which was then in uſe among the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That thô thoſe words of the Prophet ſhould imply a Permiſſion, it would only relate to the Requeſt that <hi>Naaman</hi> had made. The <hi>Syrian</hi> had only demanded of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> whether he could not give him two Mules lading of Earth of the Holy Land; and after that, he had begg'd of God, that he would pardon him, if the King leaning upon his Hand, he ſhould happen to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate himſelf together with him, in the Temple of <hi>Rimmon. Eliſha</hi> therefore anſwers to the Firſt demand, but not to the Second.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That thô the Words ſhould include the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets permiſſion, we ought not to conclude from thence, that a Man may be an Idolater, and yet reſerve his Heart immaculate for God. For that was not the Thing vvhich <hi>Naaman</hi> deſir'd of the Prophet; and thô the Prophet had granted it,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:179515:62"/>nevertheleſs we never ought to do it. Becauſe it is certain, that God has expreſly forbid Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and whatever has the leaſt Relation to it; ſo that, if not only a Prophet, but all the Angels of Heaven ſhould ſay the contrary, we ought to look upon 'em as <hi>Anathema</hi>'s. All that we are to infer from thence is this, That they who ſerve Princes are permitted to be preſent at the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of their Maſters Religion, when the Duty of their Employment obliges 'em to pay 'em any Service. And this is that which <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian</hi> did, in compliance with the Emperor <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> when he enter'd into the Temple of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune;</hi> and what in the laſt Age the Elect. of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony</hi> did, in reſpect of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the V.</p>
               <p>I add to theſe Reflexions,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is ſome Reaſon to doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may be allow'd to practiſe under the new Covenant, what might be tolerated, under the Old, in a poor Pagan, whoſe Knowledge was very ſmall, and who had had no other Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but what the Prophet had given him in his Familiar Converſation. But we may be thought to be oblig'd to greater Duties; We, that have been bred in the School of Chriſt, and are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viron'd with ſuch a Cloud of Witneſſes, who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſe to dye a thouſand times, than to do any thing that might be ill interpreted.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That No Man ought to do that which <hi>Naaman</hi> did, in deſpite of his Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if any one be oblig'd to do it, he ought not to give any occaſion for others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he approves what is done in a falſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:179515:62"/>Religion. Quite the contrary, he ought to let the World ſee, that he deteſts it, and abhors the Errors, the Worſhip, the Myſteries and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of it. This is that which <hi>Valentinian</hi> did. For <hi>Theodoret</hi> obſerves, that one day as he was attending upon <hi>Julian</hi> to the Temple of <hi>Fortune,</hi> he gave a good Cuff to the Verger that ſprinkl'd the Holy Water upon all that enter'd, becauſe he obſerv'd that a drop of Water had fall'n upon himſelf; and cry'd out aloud, that he was contaminated thereby, inſtead of being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify'd. Which ſo provoked the Emperor, that he baniſh'd <hi>Valentinian:</hi> But he remain'd not long in exile; for within a year, and ſome few Months afterwards, he became Maſter of the Empire himſelf.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I conclude, that it is much the ſafer way to renounce all thoſe Employments, then to engage our Selves in Actions contrary to our Belief; and that it's better to quit 'em, then to ſcandalize our Brethren.</p>
               <p>In the Fourth Place, the Example of St. <hi>Paul</hi> is objected, who as he teaches us himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20, 21, 22, <hi>And unto the Jews I became a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, as under the Law, that I might gain them that are under the Law; To them that are without Law, as without Law (being not without Law to God, but under the Law to Chriſt) that I might gain them that are without the Law. To the weak became I as weak, that I might gain the weak; I am made all things to all Men, that I might by all means ſave ſome.</hi> After ſo fair an Example ſet, who is there, ſay they, who would ſcruple to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:179515:63"/>conform to the Times, to the Place where he lives, and the Perſons with whom he converſes.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, that no Body denies, but that we ought to conform to Time, to Place, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; provided we do nothing againſt our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and that we acquit our ſelves of theſe Duties which the True Religion exacts from us. We ought to conform with Time and Place in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking our ſelves to flight, when we are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted; to quit our Country, and change our Habitations, till, like <hi>Joſeph, Mat.</hi> 2. we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that they who ſeek our Lives are dead. We ought to comply with perſons, to avoid the expoſing of Holy things to the Prophane, and giving occaſion of ſcandal to the weak. Thus <hi>St. Paul</hi> became a Jew to the Jews, obſerving thoſe Ceremonies among 'em, which were not contrary to the Chriſtian Faith, by circumciſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> and cauſing himſelf to be ſhaved at <hi>Cenchreas.</hi> He was under the Law to thoſe that were under the Law, in abſtaining from thoſe Ceremonies that might offend the Gentiles. Laſtly, he became weak to the weak, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with their Infirmities. Read upon this Subject, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. But that Holy Apoſtle never practis'd any baſe or treacherous compliances with any body, only he became all things to all Men, in things Permitted and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; you may Judge by his manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving <hi>St. Peter,</hi> who trode not aright, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd the Gentiles to <hi>Judai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. Gal.</hi> 2.14. What then can our Antagoniſts prove from hence? Let 'em become all things to all Men, like <hi>St. Paul,</hi> we will never blame 'em. But does it follow
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:179515:63"/>from thence, that we may embrace all Religions, abandon the True one, and profeſs a Falſe one? like that ſame <hi>Ecebolus,</hi> who was ſometimes Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, ſometimes Arrian, ſometimes Pagan. God preſerve us from any ſuch thoughts. Had St. <hi>Paul</hi> been of our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi>'s mind, would he have undergone ſo many Afflictions; expos'd himſelf to ſo many dangers; would he have ſuffer'd himſelf to be loaded with ſo many Chains; or would he have dy'd by the hand of the Common Executioner? No, without doubt, There was nothing more eaſie for him then to have avoided thoſe bitter and continual Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. He need have done no more, then to have extolled <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Jews; <hi>Jupiter, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> and the reſt of their Counterfeit Deities to the Pagans; and thus he would have pleaſed all. But then he would not have taught Jeſus Chriſt. He preaches him up every where, thô they threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him with a thouſand Torments, in the <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opagus</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> among the Jews and Gentiles; never diſſembling his Sentiments: So far from being aſhamed of the Goſpel of his Divine Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that he Preached him both boldly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and made it his chiefeſt Glory ſo to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:179515:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> An Anſwer to ſome Reaſons which are brought by our Antagoniſts.</head>
               <p>OUR <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> make ſome Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo. In the firſt place they put the Queſtion, whether God cannot ſave Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all ſorts of Religions; eſpecially ſuch as confeſs Jeſus Chriſt, and acknowledge him to be the Son of God, the Promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Crucify'd, Dead, and Riſen from the Grave. This Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Ridiculous; for the Buſineſs in Diſpute is not what God can do, nor ſhall we undertake to ſet Bounds to his Infinite Mercy. But we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe that he will ſave thoſe that depart from a Pure Communion; who abjure his Truth; who make publick Profeſſion of doing Things which they do not believe, and who Die unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant in that ſad Condition. God has ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Explained himſelf in this matter, that he muſt willingly ſeek his own Deſtruction, that flatters himſelf to obtain Mercy, and follows the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of our <hi>Indifferent Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſay they in the Second Place, is it not a hard Caſe to be deſpoil'd of our Eſtates, to be deprived of our Honours, and Conveniencies of Life, to be Baniſh'd, to renounce our Pleaſures, to live in a Comfortleſs and lonely Deſart, to be confin'd to a Dark and Loathſom Dungeon, and to die cruelly by the hand of the Hangman? I grant that this is all unpleaſing to the Fleſh. But do they not find that God ſufficiently recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:179515:64"/>thoſe who ſuffer for his ſake? That he gives 'em his Heaven, and gave 'em himſelf. Whatever the Suff'rings are to which the Lord Jeſus expoſes his Believers and his Members, are they comparable to what he ſuffer'd himſelf to purchaſe our Salvation? Or is there any Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between them and the Recompence which the Mercy of God beſtows upon us; between the Miſeries of this Life, and thoſe which we may juſtly be afraid of after Death; between the Bleſſings which it is in his Power to bereave us of, and thoſe which he has prepared for us; between the falſe Pleaſures which we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to renounce, and the ſolid Pleaſures which we hope to enjoy; between the Honours and Dignities which we quit in this World, and thoſe Eternal Glories to which we are deſigned? 'Tis a hard caſe to be perſecuted, crys the Fleſh; but is it not a happy thing to be favour'd of God, to be at peace in our Souls, to be aſſur'd of the Love of the Father of Heaven, to be Heirs of an Eternal Inheritance, to wear one day a Crown of Life, and to enjoy an endleſs Felicity? 'Tis a hard caſe to live in Adverſity; but is it not infinitely more tedious for a Man to bear about him his Accuſer, his Witneſs, his Judge, and his Executioner; to be gnaw'd by a Worm that never Dies, and to enjoy no Repoſe? It is a terrible Thing to be reduc'd to the Condition of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> but it is much more dreadful to be caſt headlong into Hell with the Wicked Rich Man, while <hi>Lazarus</hi> is receiv'd into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom. It is a hard Caſe for a Man to lay down his Life; but is it not a happineſs to loſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:179515:65"/>it for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, to the end we may live Eternally with him? What is it which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of us, which the Devil does not exact from his Slaves, thô they never can expect other from him then Eternal Miſery; and what we do not frequently do our ſelves upon wicked Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes, and to ſatisfie our Paſſions? I ſhall not extend this Diſcourſe any farther: I only beſeech God that our <hi>Indifferent Men</hi> and <hi>Libertines</hi> may ſeriouſly reflect upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Againſt thoſe who maintain, that we ought to believe what the Magiſtrates will have us believe.</head>
               <p>I Come now to thoſe who hold, that the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Law, which is to be followed as well in Sacred, as in Civil Matters, is the Law of Magiſtrates, and that every Thing is to be ſubjected to their Commands. This was the Sentiment of an Author famous once in <hi>England,</hi> and who has ſtill but too many followers. He believ'd that the Ifraelites were bound to receive for the Law of God, what <hi>Abraham</hi> delivered to 'em for the Law of God; and that the Publick Laws ſupply the Place of Conſcience to all Men. He ſaid moreover, explaining thoſe words of <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Who ſhall deny me before Men, &amp;c.</hi> That a Subject was not to be blam'd for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Chriſt, if he were thereto conſtrain'd by his Prince. I compare the Author of this Opinion to that ſame wretched Flatterer, who
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:179515:65"/>formerly propoſed, in favour of his Prince, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration importing, that nothing ſhould be look'd upon as juſt, but what the King requir'd.</p>
               <p>Nor much unlike to this was the Practiſe of thoſe Hereticks which a certain Philoſopher upbraided, that they ador'd not God, but the Imperial Pomp, changing Opinions according to the Sentiments of that Prince under whom they lived. This is an Impious Opinion, and it is very eaſie to ſhew the Falſhood of it.</p>
               <p>In a word, were there any Ground for this Opinion, there would be no longer any other Deity to be acknowledged but the Magiſtrate, under whom we are born Subjects, and we ought not to admit of any other Rule for the Conduct of our Lives, and our Manners, then the Laws of Princes. There would be no need of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our ſelves what God has reveal'd to Men, or what his Pleaſure is; but what the Magiſtrate commands us. We muſt expound the Scripture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Sentiments of the Magiſtrates under whom we Live, and not as it expounds it ſelf; as that Emperor pretended, who by an Edict ordain'd that a certain Paſſage of Scripture ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd according to his Senſe: We ought to obey 'em in deſpight of our Conſciences and the Light of Right Reaſon; and <hi>Daniel</hi> is extreamly to be blam'd, who refus'd to obey the Impious Edicts of the Prince under whom he lived. Who can hear ſuch Diſcourſes as this without trembling. Beſides, is it not ridiculous to think that Men are bereft of their Reaſon, and the knowledge of Good and Evil, ſo ſoon as they liſt themſelves in a Society, while that ſame Knowledge reſides
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:179515:66"/>only in Sovereigns; or that we ſhould be bound to do that, which we know to be a Sin.</p>
               <p>But ſay they, does not the Scripture command us to obey the Magiſtrate? 'Tis very true, nor does any Body deny it. We alſo farther believe, that we ought to be obedient to higher Powers, thô they make profeſſion of a Contrary Religion to ours; according to the Example not only of the Apoſtles, but alſo of the Fathers of the Church, and particularly of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd for having conſpir'd againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> becauſe he was a Chriſtian, and the Emperor was a Pagan, made Anſwer. <hi>We Chriſtians are ſo far from Conſpiring againſt our Emperors, that we put up our Supplications every day for</hi> Caeſar, <hi>becauſe he is our Prince, althô he Worſhip other Deities then we do.</hi> But if we believe that it behoves us to obey Magiſtrates, we add withal, that we are not bound to pay our Obedience to 'em, but in things which are not contrary to the word of God. We believe that we ought to give to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> but withal, that we ought to give to God that which is God's, as Jeſus Chriſt inſtructs us. When the Law of the Prince agrees with the Law of God, then we obey him without Scruple; but when the Princes Law does not correſpond with the Law of God, we make no difficulty to aſſert, that it is a piece of Impiety to obey that Law, becauſe it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God then Man, as the Apoſtle en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns us. What greater Affront can be put upon God, then to obey Men rather then Him, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Human Laws, and violate Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. He is the King of Kings, and Lord of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:179515:66"/>Lords; When he opens his Mouth, he alone ought to be hearkned to, and we ought not then to heed what Men ordain, when it is contrary to the Command of our Great Maſter. The Companions of <hi>Daniel</hi> were highly commended for refuſing to proſtrate themſelves before the Statue of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> though that haughty Prince had ordained it under ſevere Penalties; but the Iſraelites are blamed for having followed <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and for having abandoned the Temple of the True God. This Doctrine has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Univerſally received by all Chriſtians, and I could cite upon this Subject <hi>Tertullian,</hi> St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> &amp;c. The Popes Decretals are in Expreſs Terms. <hi>If the Lord Commands Things which are not Contrary to the Scripture, let the Servant be ſubject to his Lord; but if he Commands things contrary, let him obey the Lord of the Soul, not the Lord of the Body. If the Emperor commands what is good, execute the Command, if it be Evil, Anſwer, God is to be obey'd before Man.</hi> This is that which was practiſed by the <hi>Thebean</hi> Legion; if it be true, at leaſt what ſome Authors have written, all the Soldiers of that Legion were Chriſtians. Now after they had paſs'd the <hi>Alps,</hi> and were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching near <hi>Maximian</hi>'s Army, they Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that the Emperor, according to Cuſtom, was reſolved to make all his Soldiers ſwear Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to him, upon an Altar Conſecrated to a Counterfeit Deity, and that they were to take an Oath contrary to the Impulſes of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which having obliged 'em to draw off in a Body from the reſt of the Camp, <hi>Maximian</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:179515:67"/>ſent his Commands to 'em to come away and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the Gods; to which <hi>Mauricius,</hi> Chief of the Legion, <hi>Exuperus</hi> and <hi>Candidus,</hi> anſwered, in the name of all the reſt, That they were all ready to fight againſt the Enemies of the Empire, but that they would never ſacrifice to falſe Gods, nor act againſt their Brethren. <hi>Maximian,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd at this Anſwer, caus'd the whole Legion to be twice decimated, and every Tenth Man to be put to death; but ſeeing that would do no good, but that the Soldiers ſtill continued ſtedfaſt in their Profeſſion of the Truth, he ſent the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt that ſingle Legion, which ſurround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em on every ſide, put 'em all to the Sword; And thus, with their Blood, they ſeal'd to that Truth, That loſs of Life is to be preferr'd a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times before acting contrary to the Light of a Man's Conſcience.</p>
               <p>But in regard the Truth of this Hiſtory is call'd in queſtion, I ſhall produce another which is beyond all contradiction; which is the Story of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Soldiers. That Emperor had ſurpriz'd 'em by ordaining that they ſhould ſtrow ſome grains of Incenſe, before they received the Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſe, which he was about to beſtow upon 'em. Some of 'em being inform'd of the Fraud, the reſt did innocently what was requir'd from 'em, but being told of the fault which they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, they were not contented to come and cry out in the publick Market-place, <hi>We are Chriſtians, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, we have not renounced thee. If our Hand has committed a Crime, our Will has not conſented;</hi> But they came to the Emperor, and with exalted Voices, <hi>Reſerve,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>our Gifts
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:179515:67"/>for the Soldiers; Sacrifice us to Jeſus Chriſt who is our Monarch; Burn us in the Place where we have ſtrew'd the Incenſe; Cut off our hands that have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo great a Crime, as to ſtretch themſelves out upon your Altars. Diſtribute your Gold to thoſe who are not ſorry for having received it: Jeſus Chriſt is ſufficient for us, and ſupplies all our wants.</hi> After this, they patiently and joyfully ſuffered death, every one of them, except one who was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd by the Emperor, but who was very ſorry that he had not the Honour to abrogate his Crime by the ſame Martyrdom which his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions had undergone.</p>
               <p>But ſay they, Does not <hi>St. Paul</hi> Teach us, that we ought to ſubmit our ſelves to Princes, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake. 'Tis very true; but it does not follow from thence, that Princes or Magiſtrates have any right over the Conſcience, or that they have any Power to make us believe what they pleaſe. No Body has any Right over the Conſcience, but only he that infuſed it into Men. This is that which has been acknowledg'd in all Ages. I could eaſily prove it, would I but collect together, what has been written upon this Subject. I could cite the Fathers of the Church, <hi>Tertullian, Lactantius, St Hilarie,</hi> and <hi>St. Athanaſius.</hi> I could alſo cite ſeveral Councils, as the Fourth Council of <hi>Toledo,</hi> in the year 633. wherein there paſt a Decree in theſe words. As for the <hi>Jews, The Synod has ordain'd that from henceforth, that no body ſhall be forc'd to believe. For God has compaſſion upon whom he will have mercy, and hardens whom he pleaſes; and People are not to be ſav'd by force, but willingly;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:179515:68"/>for the better obſervance of the outward form of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, For as Man loſt himſelf by obeying the Serpent willingly, ſo is he alſo Sav'd by believing, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, when he calls him by his Grace. Let Perſuaſion therefore be made uſe of, and not violence, to incline 'em to turn freely, and without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint.</hi> And the <hi>Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Seville <hi>loudly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns that Prince, who had conſtrain'd by his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thoſe that ought to have been converted by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> To which may be added that ſame Law, of which, mention is made in the <hi>African Codex</hi> of Monſieur <hi>Juſtel,</hi> by which every one is left at his liberty, whether he will embrace the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, or not. I could alſo quote ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Emperors. For example, The Emperor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> who had deſir'd that all his Subjects might be Chriſtians, without conſtraining any body. The Emperor <hi>Jovian,</hi> who is applauded, for that he gave every body leave to profeſs what Religion he pleas'd. The Emperor <hi>Valentinian,</hi> who ſet forth Laws, by which he gave Liberty to every body to profeſs the Religion wherein he was bred. The Emperor <hi>Marcian,</hi> who in the Letter which he wrote to the <hi>Archimandrites,</hi> and the Monks of <hi>Jeruſalem, We will not hale,</hi> ſays he, <hi>or drag any Perſon, whoever he be, into the way of Truth, either by T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reats, or by Violence:</hi> and the Emperor <hi>Conſtant in Pogonatus,</hi> who in his Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon occaſion of the Sixth Univerſal Council<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he call'd at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> expreſly ſays, <hi>We could invite and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort all the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rld, to amend themſelves, and unite with the Chriſtians, but we will conſtrain no body.</hi> 'Tis true, that <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> us'd violence towards
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:179515:68"/>the <hi>Saxons;</hi> but his Conduct is blam'd be <hi>Ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his Tutor; as was alſo that of King <hi>Chilperic,</hi> by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt; and that of King <hi>Siſebut</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> by the Council of <hi>Toledo.</hi> Laſtly, I could cite the Pagans themſelves, who have been of the ſame Opinion, That no body has Right over the Conſcience, and that the Will is not to be forc'd, as appears by what was written by an <hi>Indian</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher to <hi>Alexander. Thy Friends adviſe thee to offer violence to the</hi> Indian <hi>Philoſophers: Thou mayſt remove their Bodies from one Place to another, but thou canſt never force their Minds,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There is no Prince or King that can make us do any thing againſt our Will.</hi> This is a moſt certain Truth, and they who are of another Opinion, talk againſt the Light of their Underſtandings. Thus M. <hi>Le B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et,</hi> Counſellor of State, in his Treatiſe of the King's Sovereignty, diſcuſſing the Queſtion, Whether it be Lawful ſometimes to diſobey the King? Anſwers, That in matters of Religion there is no wavering to be admitted, between the Fear of God and Man. And he alſo maintains; That in auſtere and harſh Proceedings, the Miniſter of the Prince's Cruelties participates of his Crime; and that a Judge who pronounces an unjuſt Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, reſolving upon Injuſtice, and condemns the Innocent upon privy Signet Letters, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſes in his Obedience; becauſe that being a Meſſenger of Juſtice, he never ought to abuſe it, to colour over the Fury and Iniquity of a Prince, who borrows the Formalities of it. What think ye, was the meaning of <hi>St. Paul,</hi> when he teaches us that we ought to ſubmit to Princes, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake? No
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:179515:69"/>other, without queſtion, but that we ought to ſubmit to the Higher Powers, in things which are not forbid by the Law of God, not only for Wrath, that is to ſay, becauſe there is no reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em without puniſhment, and without incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Indignation, but alſo for Conſcience ſake; that is, becauſe the word of God binds our Conſciences to it. For if we allow any greater Latitude to the words, it muſt be ſaid, that <hi>St. Paul</hi> meant, that we ſhould ſacrifice to falſe Gods, if we liv'd under a Prince that ſhould c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmand it. Which is that which no Man dares preſume to ſay; Since no Man can be ignorant of the Opinion of that faithful Servant of God in this particular. We ſay no more of it here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have already ſpoken concerning it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Againſt thoſe who believe it ſufficient to live, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules of Moral Honeſty.</head>
               <p>THere are many People who believe it to be ſufficient to live well, but that 'twas no great matter what they believ'd: that it was enough to reform their Manners, but that there was no neceſſity of tormenting a Man's ſelf about his Belief, and that he may be Sav'd in all S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts, provided he abſtains from thoſe Vices which the Law of God and right Reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn. But they who are of this Opinion, are groſly miſtaken; nor will it be a difficult thing to evince 'em.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if it be ſufficient to lead an Innocent Life, without ever troubling our ſelves what we ought
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:179515:69"/>to believe, 'tis a wonderful thing that Faith ſhould be ſo often recommended to us, and that the Holy Men of God ſhould declare, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it there is no Salvation. <hi>Amend your Lives,</hi> ſays Chriſt, but at the ſame time, <hi>believe in the Goſpel. If thou believ'ſt,</hi> ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> to the Eunuch, and he Anſwer'd, <hi>I believe that Jeſus is the Son of God. If thou confeſs with thy Mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine heart, that God has rais'd him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſav'd. But without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe him.</hi> Heb. 11.6. <hi>He that believeth in him is not condemn'd; but he that believeth not is already condemn'd; becauſe he has not believ'd in the name of the only begotten of God.</hi> And this Faith is diſtinguiſh'd from good Works, as you may find in the Epiſtles to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the <hi>Glatians,</hi> and in other Places. I confeſs, that Faith alone without Charity, is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Save. <hi>Thô I ſhould ſpeak with the Tongue; of Men and Angels, if I have not Charity, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ſounding Braſs, or a Tinkling Cymb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. And thô I have the Gift of Prophecy, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand all Miſteries and all Knowledge, and thô I have all Faith, that I could remove Mountains, and have no Charity, I am nothing,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. I confeſs alſo, that without Sanctification we cannot ſee God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. But I averr, in the Firſt place, that there is no Sanctification, where there is no Faith. 'Tis Faith that purifies the Heart. Secondly, That Faith ought to have Charity for its foundation, it ought to proceed, ſaith <hi>St. Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. <hi>From a good Conſcience, a pure Heart, and a Faith unfeigned.</hi> Faith is dead without Charity; but there is no true Charity without Faith.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:179515:70"/>
               <p n="2">II. If it be ſufficient to live morally well, I cannot conceive wherefore <hi>St. John</hi> 1 Epiſt. cap. 4. would have us try the Spirits with ſo much care, to avoid the receiving all Doctrines that are Taught us, <hi>Beloved,</hi> ſays He, <hi>Believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they are of God.</hi> And for fear leſt Men ſhould think that exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Spirits was recommended to 'em, only to try whether they taught a ſtrict or looſe Morality; the Apoſtle adds, <hi>That every Spirit that confeſſeth not that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God; but this is that Spirit of Antichriſt,</hi> &amp;c. If no Man then can be of God, unleſs he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt come in the fleſh, certainly it cannot be ſufficient to live morally well, to be ſav'd; unleſs Men think they can obtain Salvation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being of God. Moreover, whence comes it that the ſame Apoſtle in his Second Epiſtle, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the Faithful to receive into their Houſes, or to bid good ſpeed to thoſe that bring not the Doctrine of Chriſt; for it appears that he ſpeaks of the ſame <hi>Seducers,</hi> who confeſs'd not that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt was come in the Fleſh. Wherefore is it that he would have us ſtand ſo ſtrictly upon our Guards, when the buſineſs in Diſpute is about the receiving a Doctrine, or not receiving it, if it were ſufficient for a Man to correct his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be Sav'd.</p>
               <p n="3">III. I draw a Third Argument from hence, that the Doctor of the Gentiles thunders out Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema's againſt thoſe that preſs the obſervation of the Moſaic Ceremonies, thô they carefully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd the practiſe of the Moral Law. If it were ſufficient to obſerve the Decalogue; would Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity have allow'd <hi>St. Paul</hi> to Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:179515:70"/>People who believ'd in Chriſt, only that they were <hi>zealous of the Law.</hi> Acts 21.20. and who were only for joyning <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Ceremonies of the one, to the Goſpel of the other.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. If this Opinion which we oppoſe were true, whence comes it that the Scripture condemns the Unbelievers to Eternal Pains, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8. and that it excludes Idolaters out of the Kingdom of Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. There can be no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given, but only becauſe that living Morally well, is not ſufficient for the obtaining of Eternal Salvation; but that it behoves us to believe thoſe Truths which are Taught us.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, If Living according to the Rules of Moral Honeſty, were ſufficient to bring a Man to Heaven, I would fain know the Reaſon why the Apoſtles take ſo much pains to inſtruct Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Truths of the Goſpel; why do they keep ſuch a ſtir to prove that Chriſt is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that they ſpeak of his Divinity and his Croſs, two things that equally ſtumbled both the Jews, and the Gentiles? Had it not been ſufficient to have taught 'em Good Morality?</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Whence comes in to paſs, that Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſo frequently exhort us to ſuffer for their Truth; and that ſo many perſons have ſuffered Martyrdom in Defence of the Truth, of which they might have been ignorant, if we may believe our Antagoniſts, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deprived of Salvation. There would have been but very few Confeſſors and Martyrs, had Moral Honeſty been ſufficient to bring us to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Felicity.</p>
               <p>To all theſe Proofs I add this Important Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion, that we draw from the Truths of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:179515:71"/>Goſpel, which are propos'd to us to the end we ſhould believe 'em, the moſt powerful Morives that are able to engage us to Holineſs. There is nothing more prevalent to incline Men to San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, then to make known to 'em a God that loves Men, to that Degree, as to give 'em his only begotten Son: a God that abhors and deteſts Sin to that degree that he rather choſe to expoſe to Death his only Son in whom he is well pleaſed, then to leave Sin Unpuniſhed. A God that takes upon him Human Nature, and under that Nature, ſuffers a moſt Cruel Death to make an Atonement for the Sin of Men, and to ſatisfie Divine Vengeance, juſtly provoked againſt 'em.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, A God that penetrates into the moſt ſecret Folds and Concealments of the Heart, who is to raiſe the Dead, and bring 'em to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Throne, to give an Account of all their Actions. It behoves us therefore to believe, if we will live well; and to believe and live well, if we intend to be Sav'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> That the Opinion of Indifferenay in Religions has diſpleaſed almoſt all People.</head>
               <p>THere remains nothing more for me, but only to Anſwer an Argument which is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King of <hi>Siam,</hi> and which we have cited already in the Third Chapter: <q>The True God, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> who Created the Heaven and the Earth, and all the Creatures therein contained, and who has given 'em Natures and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:179515:71"/>Inclinations ſo different, had he ſo pleaſed, by giving Bodies and Souls alike to Men, could have inſpir'd into 'em the ſame Sentiments, as to what Religion it behov'd 'em to follow; and have cauſed all Nations to agree and unire under one and the ſame Law. But it ſeems that Providence permits diverſity of Sects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God takes as much delight to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with different ſorts of Worſhip, and various Ceremonies, as to be glorify'd by a Prodigious Number of Creatures, the variety of whoſe Beauty's ſet forth and Magnifies his Infinite Power.</q>
               </p>
               <p>There are ſome People who ſuffer themſelves to be dazled with this Argument; but I beſeech 'em to conſider, that it may be prov'd as well, that God takes pleaſure in the Sins which Men Commit. For it might be ſaid, that had God ſo pleaſed, by giving to Men Bodies and Souls alike, he might have infuſed into 'em the ſame Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for Virtue; but that it ſeems as if he permitted the one to be Wiſe and Virtuous, the other to be very Vicious, becauſe he takes delight in the variety of Humours and Inclinations. Now I am apt to believe there are very few that would approve ſuch a Method of Arguing.</p>
               <p>To this firſt Anſwer I may add two more. The firſt is, That there might be ſomething Plauſible in this firſt Argument of the King of <hi>Siam,</hi> if God had not really made known to Men what it was that he requir'd 'em to believe, and what they were to do. But we have proved that he has reveal'd it to 'em, and that they need no more then read the Scripture with attention, and without prejudice, to underſtand which is the True Religion.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:179515:72"/>
               <p>The Second Anſwer is, That this Argument is grounded upon a falſe Principle, that God might have inſpired into all Men the ſame Sentiments of Religion, had he not taken delight in Variety. For God is not bound to make himſelf known alike to all Men. He is abſolutely at his own Liberty in all his Works. They to whom he has reveal'd himſelf have no more cauſe to magnifie themſelves then others; and they from whom he conceals himſelf, have no cauſe to complain.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it is not to be imagined from the Opinion which the King of <hi>Siam</hi> ſeems to have concerning Indifferency in Religions, that this Sentiment derives it ſelf naturally into the Thoughts of all Men. On the other ſide, it would be eaſie to prove, that the greateſt part of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions have condemned it.</p>
               <p>The thing is clear in reſpect of the Chriſtian Religion, nor is there any need of bringing far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proofs. The Pagans were ſo fixed to their Old Opinions, that one of the moſt Learned Interpreters of <hi>Virgil</hi> obſerves, that great Care was taken both among the Athenians and the Romans, that no body introduced New Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For that Reaſon it was, that <hi>Socrates</hi> was condemned at <hi>Athens,</hi> that the Jews were expell'd <hi>Rome,</hi> and that the Books of <hi>Numa</hi> were burnt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> reports, that the Athenians inflicted grievous puniſhments upon thoſe that introduc'd new Deities, and durſt preſume ſo much as to ſpeak againſt their Law. <hi>Dioniſius</hi> of <hi>Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſus</hi> aſſerts, that not only the Greeks, but alſo the Barbarians carefully preſerv'd the Religion of their Anceſtors; and the ſame thing is reported of the Scythians and Perſians. Nevertheleſs we
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:179515:72"/>will not deny, what <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid, that it was lawful for every Body to ſerve the Deity, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Cuſtom of the Country, and that Foreign Gods were often tranſported to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Athens.</hi> But give us leave to make theſe Three Remarks. 1. That the Teſtimony of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> is of no Weight, becauſe he was Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Athens.</hi> 2. That the greateſt Part of thoſe Deities which were tranſported to <hi>Rome,</hi> were remov'd out of the Cities which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans had Beſieg'd, and were by the Prieſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, before the whole Army, to the Capital of all <hi>Italy,</hi> where they ſhould have, as they ſaid, more Temples, more Sacrifices, and more Ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. To which we may add, that they were therefore removed, becauſe it was an Opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong 'em, that all Places had their Tutelar Deities, and that they could not take Cities, till after they had removed the Gods that protected 'em. 3. That thoſe Gods which were carried to <hi>Rome, Athens,</hi> and other Places, and thoſe that were there Worſhiped under the Character of unknown Gods, are ſufficient proofs, that ſome Accident fell out, of which they believed ſome Deity, that was unknown to 'em, to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; and make it appear, that the Romans were of Opinion, that the more Gods they had in their Cities, the more Protectors they had. But from thence it does not follow that the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> believ'd, that all Religions were Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. For had they ſo thought, why did they perſecute ſo Cruelly the Chriſtians and the Jews. It is certain alſo, that they derided thoſe New Gods that were introduced, as appears by the Comedies of <hi>Ariſtophanes.</hi> To which I may add,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:179515:73"/>that the <hi>Bramiry</hi> among the Indians, who are the Ancient <hi>Brachmans,</hi> believe that every Body may be ſaved in his own Religion, provided he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low exactly the way that God has ſhewed him; but that he ſhall be Damn'd, if he purſues any other.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> 'tis very true, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſeems to favour Indifferency in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, while he ſays in his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> that every Man who lives well, who Worſhips the true God, and does good Works, whether Chriſtian or Jew, obtains the Favour of his God. Nevertheleſs, 'tis certain, that in another place he aſſerts, that the Law is the only way of Salvation, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains his Religion to be eſtabliſhed in the World by force of Arms. Indeed it would be a kind of Wonder, that the Mahometans ſhould think, that the Chriſtians could be Saved, ſeeing that the Chriſtians aver <hi>Mahomet</hi> to be an Impoſtor, and daily beg of God, that that ſame falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet may have no more followers, but that his Religion may be rooted from the Earth. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, 'tis well known, that the Turks openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Perſians. Which they would never do, if 'they thought all Religions were Indifferent.</p>
               <p>As for the Jews, the Thing is ſo certain, that he who queſtions it, muſt never have read their Writings: For they continually curſe the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and are ſo obſtinately perſuaded of the Truth of their Religion, nay more, That it is the only True Religion in the World, that there have been ſeveral who have rather choſen to die, then Violate the meaneſt precept of their Law.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
